<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christs suite to his church a sermon preached at Paules-crosse the third of October 1613 / by Thomas Myriell ...</title>
            <author>Myriell, Thomas, d. 1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07952</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100664</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23036006</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23036006</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26126</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07952)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26126)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1779:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christs suite to his church a sermon preached at Paules-crosse the third of October 1613 / by Thomas Myriell ...</title>
                  <author>Myriell, Thomas, d. 1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 108 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nathaniell Butter, and are to be sould at the signe of the pide-bull neare Saint Austines gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi]¹ [par.]⁴ A-F⁸ G⁶.</note>
                  <note>Page 95 misnumbered as 79.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Song of Solomon V, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26126:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRISTS Suite to his Church.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at <hi>Paules-Croſſe</hi> the third of <hi>October</hi> 1613.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS MYRIELL, <hi>Miniſter</hi> of Gods word at BARNET.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.20.</bibl> Behold I ſtand at the dore and knocke, if any man heare my voyce and open the dore, I vvill come in vnto him, and vvill ſup vvith him, and he vvith me.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. in Ioh. Tract. 13.</hi>
               </bibl> Chriſtus ſitientibus ſons eſt, caeco lux eſt; aperiantur oculi vt videant luce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; aperiantur fauces cordis, vt bibant fontem.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathaniell Butter,</hi> and are to be ſould at the ſigne of the pide-Bull neare Saint <hi>Auſtines</hi> gate. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26126:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26126:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable, SIR <hi>John Swinnarton,</hi> KNIGHT, Lord Mayor of the honourable Citie of LONDON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y <hi>LORD:</hi> It is a diuine ſpeach of a wel-ſpoken <hi>DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VINE,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in Math. hom. 1.</note> 
               <hi>That it might haue been wiſhed that men had not needed the helpe of Learning from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but to haue had ſo pure a
<pb facs="tcp:26126:3"/>life in all things, that in ſtead of Letters Gods grace might haue ſerued vs; and as Paper with Incke, ſo our harts with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, might haue beene imprinted with the knowledge of our duty.</hi> But ſeeing the happyeſt man that is, is not happy inough this way, our ſecond riches is, to get learning as <hi>Vlyſſes</hi>his <hi>Moly,</hi> at the hand of God, but with great trauaile and much labour. Both which, how little the beſt Schollers haue ſpared to get ſo rich a prize, may appeare, by that which ſome report of them ſelues<note n="b" place="margin">Me autem, quid pudeat qui tot annos ita viuo, vt ab illis <hi>(Studijs)</hi> nullo me vnquam tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore, aut com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum aut ociu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meum abſtrax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, aut volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas auocarit, aut deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſomnus retardarit? Cic. <hi>pro Archia Poet.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that they were ſo wedded to their ſtudies, as from the ſame no profit could entice them; no pleaſure allure them, no, nor ſleepe hinder them.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Haec ſtudia adoleſcentiam alunt, ſenectute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oblectant, ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das res ornant, aduerſis perfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium acſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, delectant domi, non impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diunt foris, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noctant nobiſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, peregrinantur, ruſticantur. Cic. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Learning, to youth, a nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment; to age, a recreation; in
<pb facs="tcp:26126:3"/>proſperity an ornament; in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity a refuge; a delight at home; no trouble abroad; but a ſweet companion at all times, in all places, to all perſons.</hi> And by that which others report of<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Valer. Maxim.</hi> lib. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his going to <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phis;</hi> of <hi>Plato</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Diog.</hi> Laert. in vita Platon.</note> his voyage to, and his iourney ouer <hi>Egipt,</hi> and <hi>Italy;</hi> of<note n="f" place="margin">Philoſtrat. <hi>vti</hi> Hieron. <hi>ad</hi> Paul.</note> 
               <hi>Apollonius</hi> his trauails to the <hi>Perſians; Scythians, Maſſagets,</hi> and other people of <hi>India,</hi> that he might ſpeake with the <hi>Brach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans:</hi> and of many other whom <hi>St. Ierome</hi> names; as alſo by the famous<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aul. Gell. Noct.</hi> Attict. lib. 6. ca. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Euclides</hi> of <hi>Megaris,</hi> who, (as <hi>Taurus</hi> had wont to tell his ſchollers) when the Athenians had made it treaſon for any Mega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Citizen to ſet his foot in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, yet aduentured in his long gowne to goe by night from his
<pb facs="tcp:26126:4"/>owne houſe to Athens, being twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty miles at leaſt, to heare and to learne of the moſt noble <hi>Socrates,</hi> the wiſeſt man liuing at that time. And laſtly, by the painefull tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes of many other, which might be named, whoſe ſoules at their returne home (as<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nazi.</hi> Orat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in laud. <hi>Caeſarij.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nazianzen</hi> tels of his brother <hi>Caeſarius</hi>) came like loaden ſhippes, fraught with all manner precious iewels of wholeſome learning.</p>
            <p>But becauſe <hi>euery man cannot goe to CORINTH,</hi> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe ſaith, God hath not giuen euery man a body patient of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, nor a minde capable of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit for the purchaſe of learning, it followes, that where it is, men ſhould not onely admire it, as a ſingular gift of God; but reſpect it, countenance it, and reward it, as
<pb facs="tcp:26126:4"/>the moſt precious iewell among men: ſo by thankfulneſſe to God honour the giuer, and by kindnes to the poſſeſſors of it, ſhew their loue to the gift.</p>
            <p>Wherein, how much your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> excels; (I meane, in louing learning in men, and incouraging men in learning) moſt men cannot but take notice, and beſt men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but take comfort. And may it pleaſe you through Gods grace thus to goe on; it is the ready way to make your greatneſſe good, and your goodneſſe great.</p>
            <p>Amongſt others whom it hath pleaſed your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, my ſelfe am one, on whom the ſplendour of your kinde fauour hath ſhined. Not that there is any ſuch deſert in me, (I am too priuy, alas, to my owne wants) or that
<pb facs="tcp:26126:5"/>I am worthy to be named the ſame day with learned men, (my ſoule knowes it, and proteſts it:) but becauſe your large goodneſſe is pleaſed to reach downe ſo low, and the bright rayes of your kinde aſpect ſtretch ſo farre, being ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in indeede, like the royall beames of the Sunne in the Firmament, that ſhines as bright in the poore man cottage as in the Kings pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.</p>
            <p>All which thankefull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of your loue, I truſt your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> takes as ſpoken without flattery. For, beſides that hee hath no neede of falſe prayſes, that abounds with true; ſo I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my diſpoſition is as contrary to that vice, as that vice is to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue it ſelfe. Onely my deſire is, not to deſerue to be accounted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull,
<pb facs="tcp:26126:5"/>to ſo worthy a <hi>Mecoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> but to giue euident and open teſtimony of my thankefull heart, for ſo many fauours, for the time paſt; leaſt I ſhould iuſtly euer after be held vnworthy of any fauour, for the time to come.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it pleaſed your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſo much to commend and approue of this ſimple <hi>SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON,</hi> I am bold to preſent it to your perſon, and to publiſh it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Name, hoping, that (as the King did by the poore-mans rootes, ſo) your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> will take this ſimple preſent in good worth, and iudge by it how well I meane toward you in thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; as the world may conceiue by this, how much you haue done to mee in kindneſſe. In which hope reſting, I craue leaue for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb facs="tcp:26126:6"/>and take leaue of writing: praying God to bleſſe you ſtill in this life; and to crowne you with bleſſedneſſe it ſelfe in the life to come. <hi>Barnet, 9. Octob. 1613.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in loue and duty <hi>Thomas Myriell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26126:6"/>
            <head>CHRISTS SVITE TO HIS CHVRCH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>CANT. 5.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Open vnto mee, my Siſter, my Loue, my Doue, my vndefiled.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hoſe three things which<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lyran.</hi> in praef ad Prou. <hi>Solom.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Empedocles</hi> affirmed to be the chiefe commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Philoſophy<note n="b" place="margin">Mobilis afflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae contemptus futurae faelicitatis appetitus, et me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis illuſtratio. Lyr. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>the contempt of this tranſitory world, the deſire of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happineſſe, and the illumination of the minde;</hi> may more iuſtly be ſaid
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26126:7"/>to commend the holy Scriptures, and word of GOD, which is the true <hi>Philoſophy</hi> or <hi>Sophie</hi> rather,<note n="c" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.17.</note> able to make a man bleſſedly wiſe for euer. For this, firſt, inlightning the minde with the brightneſſe of the knowledge of God, directly teacheth vs to contemne the world preſent, and earneſtly exhorts vs to deſire happineſſe to come. The which, as it excellently intends in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; ſo, it moſt diuinely performs by <hi>Salomon</hi> (the great Philoſopher,<note n="d" place="margin">1 King. 4.33.</note> 
               <hi>that ſpake of Beaſts, Fowles, Fiſhes, and creeping things, as alſo of trees, from the Cedar in Libanus, to the Hyſſope on the wall</hi>) in theſe three bookes of his, (truely therefore called<note n="c" place="margin">Lyr. &amp; alij.</note> 
               <hi>Sapientiall</hi>) I meane, the bookes of the <hi>Prouerbs,</hi> of the <hi>Preacher,</hi> and of the <hi>Canticles.</hi> In the firſt, hee labours to inlighten the minde, and therefore hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnes vvith <hi>Prouerbs, To know wiſedome, and inſtruction, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the words of knowledge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.2.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26126:7"/>In the ſecond hee exhorts to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the world preſent, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee ſaith, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anity of vanities, and all is vanity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Eccle.</hi> 1.1. In the third hee moues the ſoule to deſire future happineſſe, and for that cauſe to cry out to CHRIST, <hi>Let him kiſſe mee with the kiſſes of his mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.1. Whereupon the framing of theſe three bookes is much after the building of the Temple. There <hi>Solomon</hi> made, firſt, the outter Court for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then the body of the Temple for the Prieſts, and laſtly the <hi>holy</hi> of <hi>holyes</hi> for the high Prieſt. Here he ſets downe firſt, <hi>Prouerbs,</hi> for the moſtignorant: <hi>To giue vnto the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſharpnèſſe of wit, and to the Childe knowledge and diſcretion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouer. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>Prouer.</hi> 1.3. The <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> or the PREACHER, as it were for the Prieſt, the man of learning to be buſied in; and laſtly, this <hi>Song of Songs,</hi> into which, as the <hi>holy</hi> of <hi>holyes,</hi> no man muſt preſume to enter, but hee which is of a moſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26126:8"/>ſanctified Spirit, fit in ſome ſort, as an high Prieſt, to come into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>For here <hi>Solomon,</hi> vpon occaſion of his marriage with the King of Egipts daughter, moſt diuinely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the happy coniunction of Chriſt and his Church, with which hee ſeemes to be ſo rauiſhed, that the deſcription of his owne marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age ſerues him but as a <hi>ſhell</hi> to lap vp the ſweet <hi>kernell</hi> of the other in, as the Poet fitly,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Monc. in Sol. hiſt. delib. Vti habet Ioh. Pin. dereb. Solom. lib. 5. cap. 2.</note> Nil Solomonis in hoc nudum niſi nomen &amp; vmbra</l>
               <l>Carmine, nil Phariae niſi nomen et vmbra puellae.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In this whole Song, is but the bare name and ſhadow of <hi>Solomon</hi> and the King of Egipts Daughter, the body and ſubſtance is of Chriſt and the Church:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ox hominem ſonat ipſa, meros ſonat omnis amores</l>
               <l>Affectus<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hominum, contexius, Atalmus in illis,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:26126:8"/>Nucleus, et coeleſte latet ſub cortice germen.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The ſpeech indeed is of man and woman, and the bare letter ſounds humane loue and affection; but this is but the <hi>ſhell,</hi> the ſweet <hi>kernell</hi> is within in the ſenſe, where you ſhall finde more ſung of then the loue of man to woman, euen the loue of God himſelfe to man.</p>
            <p>Hence therefore all prophane eyes and eares; and come not neare. Prophane eyes, view not the ſport of the letter,<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern.</hi> ſup. cant. ſerm. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nihil enim ſerium babet literae ſeries,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> the ſeries of the letter is nothing ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Prophane eares heare not the loue-phraſes of the ſpeakers, but,<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Origen</hi> in Cant. hom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vt ſpiritualis audi ſpiritualiter ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toria verbae cantari,</hi> ſaith <hi>Origen,</hi> as a ſpirituall man conceiue of theſe amorous words, and when thou heareſt theſe louers:<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern.</hi> ſup. cant. ſerm. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non virum et foeminam, ſed verbum et animam ſentias.</hi> Thinke not on a man and a woman, but of GOD and the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26126:9"/>ſoule of man and woman both. To conclude, view not ſo much the out-ſide of the phraſe, as the inſide of the ſenſe. The letter is but the chaffe, the corne is in the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gregor.</hi> proaem. in Cant.</note> 
               <hi>fumentorum eſt paleis, hominum frumentis veſci,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory:</hi> They are but beaſts that feed on chaffe, and men which eate the corne. The letter is but the bone, the marrow is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, therefore<note n="m" place="margin">Petrus Bleſ. <hi>ſer.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Frange os literae et innenies medullam intelligentiae.</hi> Breake with mee the bone of the letter, and you ſhall finde the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of ſenſe and vnderſtanding. Which as you muſt doe in the reſt, ſo in theſe words that I haue read: <hi>Open vnto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> 
               <hi>my Siſter, my Loue, my Doue, my Vndefiled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where you ſee, one, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and commanding, praiſing, and praying. Commending and praiſing, when hee ſaith, <hi>my Siſter, my Loue, my Doue, my Vndefiled.</hi> Commanding, or praying (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26126:9"/>you will) when hee ſaith <hi>Open vnto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The queſtion yet is, who it is that ſpeakes, and to whom? This is to bee remembred, that the ſpeakers in this booke are in all but three,<note n="n" place="margin">Iun. et. <hi>Tremel.</hi> in annot. et alij.</note> the Bridegrome which is Chriſt, figured as is ſaid, by <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> the King of Iſrael. The Bride, vvhich is the Church, figured by the King of Egypts daughter, and laſtly, the friends of them both, now and then caſting in a word, as third perſons betweene the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome and his Bride. Now the vvordes read, are ſpoken by the Bridegrome to his Bride, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ouer againe by the Bride her ſelfe; partly in ioy, as commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Bridegrome for the ſweet words he beſtowed on her;<note n="o" place="margin">Lamentatio Eccleſiae, ſeipſam incuſantis, de officio non ſalis praeſtito. Iun. in annot. ad loc. <hi>Thomp.</hi> ad loc. &amp; alij.</note> part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſorrow, as condemning her ſelfe for not liſtning to the requeſt which he made vnto her.</p>
            <p>The words which he giues vnto her, are words befitting a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26126:10"/>words full of loue. <hi>My Siſter, my Loue, my Doue, my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled.</hi> He cals her firſt, his <hi>Siſter,</hi> which ſhewes how neare ſhee is to him in affinity: Secondly, his <hi>Loue,</hi> which declares how deare ſhee is to him in affection.<note n="p" place="margin">Bern. ſup. Cant. ſerm. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Soror, quia ab vno patre, Sponſa, quia in vno ſpiritu,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard;</hi> His <hi>Siſter,</hi> as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the ſame father; his <hi>Loue,</hi> as liuing by the ſame ſpirit. Thirdly, his <hi>Doue,</hi> which ſhewes that ſhe is ſpightleſſe. Fourthly, his vndefiled, which declares that ſhe is ſpotleſſe.<note n="q" place="margin">Iſidor. Hiſp. comment. ad loc.</note> 
               <hi>Columba, quia ſpiritus ſui done illuſtrata,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſidore, Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culata, quia ſola aſpectu ſui digna.</hi> His <hi>Doue,</hi> as onely <hi>graced</hi> with his ſpirit on earth; his <hi>vndefiled,</hi> as onely <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified</hi> with his preſence in heauen.</p>
            <p>Againe, the requeſt hee makes vnto her is reaſonable. <hi>[Open vnto mee.] Open,</hi> what more eaſie in the attempt? <hi>vnto me,</hi> what more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in the intent? <hi>Open vnto mee:</hi> for I haue both done good to thee,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26126:10"/>and ſuffered euill for thee: done good to thee, whileſt I haue marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee, and made thee a Queene: Suffered euill for thee,<note n="r" place="margin">Nullum malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aut incommodum defugi, quin ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceperim propter te. <hi>Iun. annot. ad loc.</hi>
               </note> by wayting abroad ſo long till <hi>My head is wet with the dewe, and my lockes with the drops of the night.</hi> Iuſtly therefore may ſhee complaine, that ſhee was eyther ſo drowſie, as not to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at ſo kinde intreatie, or ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, as not to yeeld to ſo iuſt a demand. To begin with the firſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>My Siſter.</head>
               <p>THE Church in Scripture is vſually compared to a woman, and their analogie is apparant ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in the manner of their birth. The firſt woman<note n="s" place="margin">Gen. 2.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Eue</hi> was built out of <hi>Adams</hi> ſide whilſt he lay aſleepe. This woman, the <hi>Church,</hi> had her<note n="t" place="margin">Eccleſia enim coniux domini, facta eſt de late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, quomodo Eua illa facta eſt de latere. <hi>Auguſt. in Pſal. 126.</hi>
                  </note> birth and building too out of Chriſts ſide, which is the ſecond
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26126:11"/>
                  <hi>Adam,</hi> in his ſleepe of death vpon the Croſſe. The Souldier with a Speare pierced Chriſts ſide, and<note n="v" place="margin">Iohn 19.34.</note> 
                  <hi>immediately there came out bloud and water, Ioh.</hi> 19.34.<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in <hi>Iohan.</hi> hom. 84.</note> 
                  <hi>Non caſu, &amp; ſimpliciter hi fontes ſcaturierunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſt. Sed quoniam ex am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bobus Eccleſia conſtituta eſt:</hi> This came not to paſſe by a ſimple chance, but becauſe by theſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines the Church liues, drinking water in Baptiſme, and bloud in the Lords Supper. So that as<note n="x" place="margin">Numb. 20.11</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtrake the Rocke, and preſently there flowed out water that cheared the Iſraelites in the deſert, <hi>Num.</hi> 20.11. euen ſo <hi>Longinus</hi> ſtrake the rock Chriſt Ieſus, and immediately there flowed out the two Sacramentall ſtreames that<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 46.6.</note> 
                  <hi>make glad the Citie of God,</hi> and preſerues life in it for euermore.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the account of their husbands. <hi>Adam</hi> ioyed in his <hi>Eue,</hi> reſted in her loue, and prized her more then the whole world that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26126:11"/>GOD had giuen him before. So hath Chriſt done by his Church; he hath ioyed in her more then in all things beſide, yea, more then in himſelfe. Shee is that<note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 24.67.</note> 
                  <hi>Rebeccah,</hi> which hee like <hi>Iſaac</hi> hath brought into his owne Tabernacle, and ſets his minde on her ſo much, as for her loue hee hath forgotten the death of his Mother, the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, and ſports himſelfe alone with her, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.67. Shee that<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 24.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Rachel</hi> ſo much prized aboue bleare-eyed<note n="b" place="margin">Leah <hi>populus veſter eſt &amp; Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoga,</hi> Rachel <hi>vero noſtra Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia.</hi> Iuſt. Mart. colloq. cum Tryph.</note> 
                  <hi>Leah</hi> her Siſter, for whom, like <hi>Iacob,</hi> hee hath ſerued not ſeauen yeeres, but almoſt fiue times ſeauen, and they ſeemed ſhort vnto him becauſe hee loued her, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.20. Shee, that<note n="c" place="margin">Eſther 2.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſther,</hi> to whom Chriſt, our <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> hath held out the Scepter of peace, and hath made of a <hi>Captiue</hi> a <hi>Queene,</hi> in the roome of rebellious <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſhti,</hi> the ſtiffe-necked Synagogue. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 2.17.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in the end of their crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The woman at firſt was made
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26126:12"/>to be an help to man, her Lord, and ſuch an helpe, as ſhould be<note n="d" place="margin">Septnag. Gen. 2.18.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, euermore at his elbow, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring and ſeruing, to expell ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row from him, and to bring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to him: ſo is the Church made to<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 45.11.</note> ſerue her Lord, Chriſt; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.11. <hi>Hee is thy Lord God, and worſhip thou him:</hi> For, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the womans creation, though all creatures ſerued <hi>Adam,</hi> and were ready attendants on him, yet none was found worthy to ioyne with him in friendſhip (a thing na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally deſired of man, who is<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſt.</hi> eth. lib. 8. cap. 1.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a creature deſirous of Friendſhip) or if in friendſhip, yet by no meanes in wed-locke, which hee notwithſtanding, (being<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſt.</hi> ib. lib. 8. cap. 12.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, more naturally inclined to loue a wife in a houſe, then a friend in a citie) deſires aboue all other things. Euen ſo, although Infidels and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates, like beaſts as they are, cannot but ſerue Chriſt in the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26126:12"/>forth of his Iuſtice: yet no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice is worthy of his loue, nor plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to his minde, but onely the ſeruice of his Church, with whom hee dwels, by his grace, on earth, and who is to dwell with him in his glory, in heauen.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, in the ſeuerall eſtates and conditions that are incident to a woman. For, there is no ſtate hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening to a woman in nature, but the ſame is ſuiting to the Church in reſemblance. Thus the Church is an hand-maid, a miſtreſſe, a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a daughter, a wife, a widow, a virgin, a Spouſe, and to conclude, a ſiſter.</p>
               <p>Shee is an hand-maid, waiting and attending on Gods Seruice. Therefore thoſe words,<note place="margin">Pſal. 123.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123.2. <hi>Behold, as the eyes of Seruants looke to the hands of their Maſters, and the eyes of an hand-maid vnto the hands of her Miſtreſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in Pſal. 122.</note> 
                  <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith, are ſpoken of the Church, which is <hi>Seruus, quia
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26126:13"/>populus, ancilla quia Eccleſia:</hi> Gods Seruant, becauſe his people, Gods Hand-maid becauſe his Church: And wee which are of his familie, muſt loue him and his Church, but after a different manner,<note n="i" place="margin">Aug. in Pſ. <hi>88.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Illum ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut Dominum, hanc ſicut Ancillam,</hi> him as our Lord, her, as his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid.</p>
               <p>And yet ſhee is alſo a Miſtris. A Miſtris to rule and guide her folke, yea and to correct them too, if they doe offend. Therefore the ſame<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. epiſ. 48.</hi> Nonne contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ancillam <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> potius afflige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat? &amp;c.</note> S Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> compares her to <hi>Sarah,</hi> who when her hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayd contemned her, thruſt her out of dores,<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 21.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 21.14. So the CHVRCH <hi>foras mittit</hi> puts out of dores, by Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, ſuch as be rebellious and contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious againſt her. True it is, ſome men cannot indure to heare of this, that the Church ſhould be their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris. Hence it is, that they neglect her commaunds, and contemne her cenſures. And by their example it is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26126:13"/>come to paſſe that euery wicked liuer thinks of excommunication as <hi>brutum fulmen,</hi> or a bullet of Corke, and forgets the power of binding &amp; looſing that is committed to the Church. So that eccleſiaſticall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, which<note n="m" place="margin">Diſciplina cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos ſpei, retina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum fidei, dux itineris ſalutaris, fomes ac nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum bonae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolis, &amp;c. <hi>Cyp.</hi> de diſc. &amp; hab. Virg.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> calles, the <hi>preſeruer of hope, the retainer of faith, the guide to ſaluation, the cheriſher of good towardlines, the miſtris of vertue &amp;c.</hi> is almoſt fallen to the ground, and hath loſt his due reputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt wicked men. The Church they thinke ſhould not conſtraine, but intreate, not compell, but coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>donatiſticall</hi> opinion is confuted: firſt, by reaſon, becauſe,<note n="n" place="margin">Aug. <hi>ad</hi> Vinc. Epiſt. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Non omnis qui parcit eſt amicus, nec omnis qui verberat inimicus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtine,</hi> Not euery one that ſpareth is a friend, nor euery one that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth, an enemy. There is as well a puniſhing mercy, as a ſparing cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty. For when mildneſſe will doe no good, wee muſt vſe ſeuerity.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26126:14"/>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Hier. ad. Helio.</note> 
                  <hi>Debet amor laeſus iraſci,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierome,</hi> loue too much prouoked muſt grow angry,<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron.</hi> ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui rogantem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempſerat, audiat obiurgantem:</hi> Hee which contemned one praying, let him heare him chiding. Secondly, by example, and that euen of God himſelfe,<note n="q" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.6.</note> who <hi>caſts downe</hi> that <hi>hee may lift vp,</hi> killeth that hee may make aliue, turnes downe to hell that hee may exalt to heauen. As alſo of all good men; for<note n="r" place="margin">Aug. ad Vinc. epiſt. <hi>48.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Semper, et mali perſecuti ſunt bonos, et boni malos,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> It hath euer beene ſeene, that euill men haue perſecuted the good, and the good haue perſecuted euill men.<note n="s" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Illi nocendo per iniuſtitiam, hi conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendo per diſciplinam.</hi> The one by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice hurting, the other by diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline amending. Thus the Apoſtles being deliuered<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 10.17. <hi>Aug. vt ſupra.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>poteſtati humanae,</hi> to the power of men, deliuered their deliuerers<note n="v" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>poteſtati Satanae,</hi> to the power of Satan.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:26126:14"/>The Church is a Mother.<note n="u" place="margin">Gal. 4.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.26. <hi>Ieruſalem which is aboue is free, which is the mother of vs all.</hi> She it is that brings forth in faith, and brings vp in loue.<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypryan.</hi> de vnitat. Eccleſ. <hi>§ 5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Illius foetu naſcimur, illius lacte nutrimur, ſpiritu cius animamur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian.</hi> By her trauaile are we borne, nouriſhed by her milke, and quickned by her ſpirit. Hence that reſolute ſpeach of ſo many<note n="y" place="margin">Auguſt. Hierom. Cyprian, &amp;c.</note> Fathers: he can neuer haue God for his father in heauen, that doth not acknowledge the Church his mother on earth. Her care is great for her ſonnes, which if they proue rebellious, eyther in opinion, as Heretikes, or in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as reprobates, ſhe complaines with God,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.2. <hi>I haue nouriſhed vp children, but they haue rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</hi> Or with the Synagogue, 2 <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 2.3. <hi>I brought you vp with ioy and gladneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Eſdr. 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>but with ſorrow and heauineſſe haue I loft you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She is alſo a daughter. <hi>Sion</hi> was called ſo:<note n="z" place="margin">Zach. 9.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Tell ye the daughters of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26126:15"/>Sion.</hi> And the Church of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 45.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Hearken O daughter, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider.</hi> For if each faithfull ſoule be Gods daughter, as being borne of him, from aboue; then much more the Church, vvhich is,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper Cant. Serm. <hi>61.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Multarum vnitas, vel potius vnanimitas anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;</hi> the vnitie or rather vnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of many ſoules together. And ſhe is a daughter to God,<note n="c" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 44.</note> 
                  <hi>Quia ipſe ipſam regenerauit, &amp; ipſe quoque eam deſpondit,</hi> ſayth <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> becauſe he hath begotten her after his owne image, and becauſe he hath betroa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed her to his owne sonne.</p>
               <p>Againe, the Church is a Wife; and that by a perfect Matrymonie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Chriſt and her. For whether you take matrimony from<note n="d" place="margin">Tho. Aquin. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 44. <hi>a.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Matris munium,</hi> a Mothers Office; or from<note n="e" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Matrem muniens,</hi> a Mothers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; or from<note n="f" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Matre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> monens,</hi> from admoniſhing a Mother; or laſtly, from<note n="g" place="margin">Id. ibid. ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>materia</hi> and <hi>monos;</hi> vnitie of matter: it agreeth to Chriſt &amp; the Church excellently wel. She hauing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26126:15"/>an office vnder Chriſt to inſtruct her children well, &amp; an admonition from Chriſt, to demeane her ſelfe well; &amp; a defence in Chriſt againſt the gates of hell; and an intereſt in Chriſt to the ioyes of Heauen. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him by deputation to gouerne his ſeruants, with him by imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to partake of his inheritance.</p>
               <p>Shee is alſo a Widow: a Widow ſayth <hi>Gregory,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Greg. <hi>Moral. lib.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Quae occiſi viri ſui, interim viſione priuata eſt.</hi> Whoſe Husband Chriſt being dead, ſhee marries no more to the delights of the World, but mourneth for want of his viſion in Heauen. Therefore ſhee doth, ſayth<note n="i" place="margin">Auguſt. in 50. <hi>Homil. Hom.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> like the Widdow of <hi>Sareptah,</hi> eates her meale with reſolution to die, that being once dead ſhe may liue for euer. To this end ſhe is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering two ſtickes,<note n="k" place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quia duo ligna Crucem faciunt,</hi> becauſe two ſticks make a Croſſe, which is her onely ſtay, whereon to reſt her ſelfe in this vale of miſerie. All her meate
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26126:16"/>is the meale of Chriſts fleſh, and the oyle of his blood, which being bleſſed vnto her by the Prophets of God, feeds her, and her ſonnes, and the Prophets to.</p>
               <p>This Church is alſo a Virgine: For though, ſayth<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de verbis Dom ſer. <hi>32.</hi> Tota Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia quae conſtat ex pueris, &amp; virginibus, &amp; maritatis faemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, &amp; vxoratis viris, vno no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine virgo eſt appellata.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> She conſiſts of diuers conditions, of men, women, children and maydes, yet is ſhee commonly called by the one name of a Virgine. And the reſemblance ſtands many wayes: Firſt, In regard of puritie,<note n="m" place="margin">Auguſt. in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas carnis, corpus intactum, virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas mentis fides incorrupta.</hi> The vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie of the body is puritie of fleſh, the virginitie of the Church, is integritie of Fayth. Secondly, In reſpect of innocency: for virginity is a harmeleſſe eſtate; it is<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprian.</hi> de bono pudicit.</note> 
                  <hi>Perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans infantia,</hi> ſayth <hi>Cyprian;</hi> A perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall infancie. And the Church is a company of new-borne<note n="o" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> Babes, feeding vpon the ſincere Milke of the word, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. Thirdly, In reſpect of beauty; we all know that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26126:16"/>beautie is in virgins, as in her proper ſubiect. Therefore virginitie is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a flower:<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyp.</hi> de diſcip. &amp; habit. virg.</note> 
                  <hi>Flos eſt ille Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtici germinis, decus at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ornamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum gratiae ſpiritualis.</hi> Chaſte vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie is the flower of all Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall branches, and the comely ornament of ſpirituall grace. So is the Church her ſelfe, euen by Chriſts owne verdict, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.7.<note n="q" place="margin">Cant. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou art all fayre my loue, thou art all faire, and there is no ſpot in thee.</hi> Fourthly, In reſpect of chaſtitie. Therefore<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Digna viginitas quae apibus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paretur.</hi> Ambr. de virg. lib. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> compared a virgine to a Bee, which creature is in the<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pierius</hi> lib. 26.</note> hieroglyphicke of chaſtitie. So the Church is a chaſte virgine, preſented by the Miniſters vnto Chriſt without ſpot or wrinckle; yet in the midſt of her chaſtitie ſhee is farre from barrenneſſe:<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyp.</hi> de bono pudic.</note> 
                  <hi>Non habet faecunditatem, ſed non habet orbita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian;</hi> She hath no fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, and yet is void of barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Shee hath no children of the fleſh, but ſhe hath the off-ſpring of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26126:17"/>the Spirit.<note n="v" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambr.</hi> de vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. lib. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Partus virginis faetus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biorum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> The vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins Iſſue is the calues of the lips. Therefore <hi>Anſelme</hi> compares the<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſel.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in 2 Cor. 11.</note> Virgin Church our mother, to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> Chriſts mother. For as ſhe though a Virgin, brought forth the faireſt Child that euer was, ſo the Church a Virgin, daily brings forth to God the moſt acceptable iſſue that can be.</p>
               <p>This Virgin the Church is alſo <hi>Sponſa,</hi> that is, a Virgin affianced. A Spouſe promiſed and ſet apart to the marriage of Chriſt. <hi>Reu.</hi> 21.2. <hi>The new Ieruſalem comes downe from heauen</hi> (for her birth is from aboue) <hi>like a Bride trimmed for her huſband.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 21.2.</note> Trimmed I ſay, but at the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gromes coſt, who hath adorned her with graces,<note n="x" place="margin">Iſa. 61.10.</note> 
                  <hi>tanquam monilibus,</hi> as with precious Iewels, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.10. Shee it is that is ſo arrayed with all manner of flowers, that ſhe is ſtaid vp with flowers, amongſt which yet there is not a fairer flower then is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26126:17"/>her ſelfe. It is well obſerued by<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard.</hi> ſuper Cant. ſer. 47.</note> 
                  <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> that <hi>Solomon</hi> in this Booke, makes mention of three ſorts of flowers.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Flos campi:</hi> The flower of the field, and that is Chriſt,<note n="z" place="margin">
                        <hi>Bernard.</hi> ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>nec ſulca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus vomere, nec defoſſus ſarculo, &amp;c.</hi> whoſe fleſh was not eared with the ſhare of any humane information, nor minde tilled with the cultor of any maſters inſtruction, and yet yeelds forth the ſmell of all moſt fragrant vertues.</item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Flos horti:</hi> The flower of the garden, and that is the Church, which is digged by the knowledge of the Law, planted by the worke of the Miniſterie, watered by the preaching of the Goſpell, and fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the wall of the Sacraments.</item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Flos thalami:</hi> The flower of the bed-chamber, and that is<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Conſcientia bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis refarta operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi> Ber. ſuꝑ. Cant. ſer. 15.</note> the ſoule, filled with good works, which are the flowers that the Bride decks her ſelfe with, and deckes her ſelfe with them euery day. For ſhee is
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26126:18"/>euery day a Bride, and euery day puts on freſh flowers of good workes.<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Bern.</hi> ibid.</note> Otherwiſe <hi>Cito iacet &amp; marcet flos boni operis</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> in breui omnis ex eo extermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; nitor &amp; vigor:</hi> ſoone dies and withers the flower of a good worke, and fayles both in ſauour and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, if it be not eftſoones renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed afreſh. But of all flowers, this Bride the Church is moſt of all adorned wth Lillies and Roſes, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and Martyrs, the one where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath the white flower of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent life, the other the red flower of a bloudy death.<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Cypr.</hi> ad mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres. epiſt. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>O beatam Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam noſtram,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian;</hi> O bleſſed Church that wee haue: <hi>Floribus eius nec Lillia nec Roſae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt;</hi> her flowers want neyther Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies nor Roſes. All men ſtriue now to wreathe themſelues garlands, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note n="d" place="margin">Aut de opere candidas, aut de paſſione purpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas. <hi>Cyp. vt ſup.</hi>
                     </note> white by action, or purple by paſſion. And ſure the Church was then in her flowers indeed, the ſweet ſmell whereof hath reached to our
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26126:18"/>dayes, and ſhall continue to the end of the world.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Laſtly, the Church is Chriſts <hi>Siſter:</hi> not a Siſter by ſimilitude or imitation onely, but<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſid. Hiſp.</hi> orig. lib. 9. cap. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>germana,</hi> that is, <hi>ex eadem genitrice manaens</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iſidore</hi>) borne as it were both in a belly. For, there is a greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinitie betweene Chriſt and man, then betweene the Angels and Chriſt: for, the<note n="f" place="margin">Iob. 1.6.</note> Angels indeede are Gods progenie, and ſo Chriſt is their brother by the Fathers ſide: but to man he is allyed nearer; for man is of Gods linage,<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 17.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Ipſius genus ſumus, Acts</hi> 17.17. Wee are his ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration: and Chriſt againe is of mans linage,<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Borne of the Seede of Dauid according to the fleſh, Rom.</hi> 1.3. So that, as God made our ſoule of him, ſo hath hee made his body of vs. And the affinitie is continued both wayes: for, as GOD gaue his daughter, that is, his image to man, ſo hath hee taken mans ſiiſter, that is, his nature, in marriage to his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26126:19"/>Sonne. Iuſtly therefore doth he call the Church, and in the Church each faithfull ſoule, his <hi>Siſter,</hi> as tyed to him in a moſt firme bond of alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and conſanguinitie.</p>
               <p>And by this further you may ſee two other points. Firſt, the chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his loue vnto her. Hee cals her his <hi>Siſter,</hi> ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron.</hi> aduerſ. <hi>Iouinian.</hi> lib. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Ierome, vt tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leretur ſuſpicio foedi amoris,</hi> to take away the ſuſpition of vnchaſte loue. For the name of <hi>Siſter</hi> implies a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of fleſhly impuritie, which made him to ſay,<note n="k" place="margin">Plautus.</note> 
                  <hi>Tam a me pudica eſt, quam mea ſi ſoror ſis:</hi> Shee is as chaſte for mee, as if ſhee were my <hi>Siſter.</hi> Secondly, the greatneſſe of his loue vnto her, as being tyed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a double band; of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinitie, which makes them one bloud; and Matrimonie, which makes them one fleſh. This <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> is a brother and husband to his <hi>Sarah.</hi> How can ſhee doubt to receiue anything from God, whom ſhee hath ſo ſurely and nearely tyed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:26126:19"/>to her.<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper Cant. ſer. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Puto me iam ſpernere non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit, os ex oſſibus meis, &amp; caro de carne mea:</hi> Now verily, I thinke he can neuer deſpiſe me, which is fleſh of my fleſh, and bone of my bone. For, if hee neglect me as a brother, yet will he loue me as a husband. And thus much of the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>My Loue.</head>
               <p>AS of all Societies none is ſo neere as that of man and wife; ſo, neyther amongſt any is loue ſo feruent as betweene them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt being by ſpirituall mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage made one with his Church, and louing her more tenderly then the kindeſt husband the kindeſt wife, cals her, as ſome tranſlate it, <hi>Proximam;</hi> his neereſt: but as the<note n="m" place="margin">Paguin. Vatablus. Montan. Tremellius. &amp;c.</note> moſt and the beſt, <hi>Amicam,</hi> his deareſt: as if he were by loue gone out of himſelfe, and turned wholy into her: according to that of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26126:20"/>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Anima verius eſt vhi amat, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vbi animat.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> The Soule is rather where it loueth then where it liueth. And ſo indeed it is with God, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſup. cant. ſerm. <hi>59.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quia amorem non tam habet quam hoc ipſe eſt,</hi> becauſe hee cannot be ſaid ſo much to haue loue, as to be euen loue it ſelfe. Hence it is, that he hath put off his roabes of Maieſtie, and cloathed himſelfe with our fleſh, and ſo is become the ſame with his Church on earth, that his Church might become the ſame with him in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Neuer louer ſo changed like him, and therefore neuer loue ſo vnchangeable as his.</p>
               <p>Here then haue wee iuſt occaſion miniſtred, to conſider of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his loue to the Church, who cals the Church his <hi>Loue.</hi> A theame, I confeſſe, admirably diſcuſſed by incomparable Diuines; after whom yet, giue mee leaue to throw my mite, and to ſay ſomething of that, of which we can neuer ſay enough.</p>
               <p>It is commonly ſeene, that loue
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26126:20"/>is manifeſted foure wayes: Firſt, by word of mouth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and this is the leaſt and ſmalleſt meaſure of ſhewing loue. Euery diſſembler will loue <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo tenus,</hi> in tongue and in word, though not in deede and veritie. There is therefore a ſecond degree, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and that is by beſtowing benefits. And this is ſome point of loue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede. For,<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg.</hi> in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uang. hom. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Probatio dilectionis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitio eſt operis,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) The commendation of true loue, is the performance of ſome good turne. But becauſe gifts are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times beſtowed as much for ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, as for loue of a friend (when a man by giuing ſomewhat, hopes to receiue much more) therefore there is a third degree greater then the other, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and that is by perſonall ſeruice, when a man is not onely content to part with his goods, but to impart his labours, and ſuffer paine himſelfe, that his Loue may inioy pleaſure. And though this be as much as can be deſired, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> yet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:26126:21"/>there is one degree further, and that is by ſuffering death for the party beloued. And here loue and all hath his end ſo that hee which hath this can deſire no more.</p>
               <p>Now all theſe wayes hath God loued his Church: for, firſt, how amiably doth hee vſe her in words for her owne good? words of ſweet Epithets,<note n="q" place="margin">Can. 5.2.</note> 
                  <hi>My Siſter, my Loue, my Doue, my Vndefiled.</hi> Of kinde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty;<note n="r" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> 
                  <hi>We pray you in Gods ſtead, euen as if God did beſeech you through vs, that yee be reconciled vnto God.</hi> Of wholeſome admonition;<note n="s" place="margin">Ezek. 18.31.</note> 
                  <hi>Caſt away from you all your vngodlineſſe, why will yee dye O yee houſe of Iſrael, ſeeing I haue no pleaſure in the death of a ſinner?</hi> Of ſound aduiſe;<note n="t" place="margin">Reuel. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>I coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell thee to buy of mee, gold tryed by the fire, that thou maiſt be made rich.</hi> And laſtly, of alluring prouocation;<note n="v" place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Come vnto mee all yee that are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie laden, and I will refreſh you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſecond: How hath hee ſpent his gifts vpon vs? In the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:26126:21"/>hee gaue vs our ſelues, and all things neceſſary for our ſelues. He diuided his ſubſtance to man, his youngeſt ſonne; and when hee like a prodigall had ſpent all, how did he receiue him againe?<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sence.</hi> de ira, lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nimis nos ſuſpicimus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca, ſi digni nobis videmur, &amp;c.</hi> wee are too much in loue with our ſelues, if euer we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that we are worthy that the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens ſhould moue for vs, Sun and Moone ſhine to vs, raine and dew fall on vs, earth and ſea feede and comfort vs. How much more then vnworthy are wee, that after all this, God ſhould beſtow his ſonne on vs; his onely ſonne on vs his fugitiue ſeruants? In the creation hee gaue vs the beſt things that he had, when as yet wee had nothing of our owne; but in the reſtauration hee makes an exchange with vs,<note n="x" place="margin">In primis de ſuis meliora contulit in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundis de noſtris inferiora ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Tempor. ſer. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> hee takes the <hi>worst</hi> things that wee haue, and hee giues vs the <hi>beſt</hi> things that he hath. Hee takes our <hi>nature,</hi> and giues vs his <hi>grace:</hi> hee takes our <hi>fleſh,</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26126:22"/>giues vs his <hi>ſpirit:</hi> hee takes our <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery,</hi> and giues vs his <hi>mercy:</hi> he takes our <hi>pouerty,</hi> and giues vs his <hi>riches:</hi> hee takes our <hi>ſhame,</hi> and giues vs his <hi>glory:</hi> finally, hee takes our <hi>croſſe,</hi> and giues vs his <hi>crowne:</hi> our <hi>death,</hi> and giues vs his <hi>life.</hi> For in giuing vs his Sonne, hee giues vs all things that can be deſired. And neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did God giue a gift like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, infinite: then hee did. Novv verily a moſt worthy gift, as hee is of moſt worth that is the giuer.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he hath not beene plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed alone to beſtow benefites on vs, but in his owne perſon hath come and ſerued for vs, yea hath ſerued vs.<note n="y" place="margin">Math. 20.28.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſonne of man came not to be miniſtred vnto but to miniſter, Math.</hi> 20.28. Euen hee which is Lord of all, made himſelfe ſeruant vnto all.<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> ſup. cant ſer. <hi>64.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quae est iſta quaeſo vis, tam violenta ad victoriam, tam victa ad violentiam?</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi> What force is that, which moued him who of himſelfe is ſo violent in all victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26126:22"/>for man yet, to be ſo vanquiſhed with all violence.<note n="a" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Amor eſt.</hi> It is nothing elſe but the force of loue. This made him to<note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>take on him the forme of a ſeruant. Philip.</hi> 2.7. Yea,<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> ter. quart. Heb. poenoſ.</note> 
                  <hi>non ſolum ſerui vt ſubeſſet, ſed quaſi mali ſerui vt vapularet,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi> not the forme of a ſeruant onely to bee in ſubiection, but of a bad ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to beare correction. And which is more yet, to be made a compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of beaſts, <hi>borne in a Stable;</hi> and which is moſt of all, to bee made as it were prouender for beaſts, <hi>laid in a manger.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> ſup. cant. ſerm.</note> 
                  <hi>Cibus hominis mutauit ſe in pabulum pecoris, homine mutato in pecus.</hi> When man was become a beaſt, Chriſt would become as it were prouender to feede him.</p>
               <p>But all this Chriſt thought not inough for vs, vnleſſe hee dyed for vs. So great a degree of loue, as there could bee no greater, which makes his loue ſo much more ſweet, as the looſing of life it ſelfe is accounted bitter. For it is a truth, euen which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:26126:23"/>comes from the author of vntruth;<note n="e" place="margin">Iob 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Skinne for ſkinne, and all that a man hath will hee giue for his life. Skinne for ſkinne,</hi> that is, the skinne or life of a mans children or cattell for his owne skinne,<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lyran.</hi> annot. in Iob 2.</note> as <hi>Lyra</hi> expounds it. Or <hi>skinne for skinne,</hi> that is, the more hard skinne for the more tender skinne; as when a man catcheth a blow on his hand to ſaue his eye, as<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Strab.</hi> in gloſſ. ordin.</note> 
                  <hi>Strabus</hi> interprets it. For there is nothing that a man had not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endure then loſſe of life. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry creature, as<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de ciuit. dei. lib. 11. cap. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Augustine</hi> obſerues, hath ſuch a loue to haue a being, that it had rather be, though in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, then not be at all. Wonderfull therefore and vnſpeakeable is the loue of Chriſt Ieſus to his Church, who ſo willingly, and ſo ioyfully ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered euen the moſt ſhamefull and bitter death for her ſake. Men may coldly and ſlightly thinke of it, but principalities and powers ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed at it.</p>
               <p>That you may yet take a further
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:26126:23"/>view of it, compare his loue with the loue of other perſons, and you ſhall ſee how farre hee goes before them all. Loue is moſt feruent among foure ſorts of couples. 1. Betweene friend and friend, which are as one heart in two bodyes. 2. Betweene the parent and the childe, which are as two bodyes from one ſtocke. 3. Betweene the husband and the wife, which are as two perſons in one fleſh. 4. Betweene the body and the ſoule, which are as two ſubſtances in one perſon. Now the loue of Chriſt to his Church exceedes the loue of all theſe each to other.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it exceedes the loue that is betweene friend and friend. For what man is there which loues an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſo as he could be contented to dye for him? yes,<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 5.7.</note> 
                  <hi>peraduenture,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, for a good man one would dye.</hi> It may be <hi>Damon</hi> would haue done it for <hi>Pythias, Pylades</hi> for <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtes.</hi> And this is as much as euer any man did, or can doe: For,<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 15.15.</note> 
                  <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:26126:24"/>loue then this hath no man, that one ſhould giue his life for his friend.</hi> But CHIRST, ſaith <hi>Paul, ſetteth forth his loue vnto vs,</hi> that<note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>cum inimici eſſemus,</hi> when wee were his enimies hee was content to dye for vs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. Hee loued vs<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſup. cant. ſerm. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>non existentes, imo &amp; reſiſtentes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> when wee were nothing, and when wee were worſe then nothing; when wee were his very foes, and mortall enemies. If it bee ſaid they are all Chriſts friends for whom he dyed, we muſt anſwere vvith a father, hee dyed indeed<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> in Pſal. Qui habitat?</note> 
                  <hi>Pio iam amicis, nondum quidem amantibus, ſed tamen iam amatis,</hi> for his friends indeede, as being heartily loued of CHRIST, though like vnkinde friends they loued him not againe.<note n="o" place="margin">Tho. Aqui. <hi>in</hi> Iohannem, <hi>vti</hi> Barrad. <hi>to.</hi> 4 <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Non amici quaſi amantes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Thomas, tantum amici vt amati.</hi> Not his friends as louing him any thing, onely his friends as loued by him alone.</p>
               <p>Againe it exceedes the loue that is betweene the parent and the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:26126:24"/>childe. For what father in the world hauing but one onely ſon, would be content to put him to death, he not deſeruing it, to pleaſure others?<note n="p" place="margin">Eſa. 49.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Can a woman forget her child, &amp; not think vpon the fruit of her wombe?</hi> You will ſay, <hi>Abraham</hi> would haue done it for loue to God. Indeede he is ſingular in this caſe, and ſuch an example, as the vvorld neuer afforded the like.<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen</hi> in Geneſ. hom. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Origen</hi> ſets it our thus.<note n="r" place="margin">Geneſ. 22.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Take,</hi> ſaith God <hi>thine onely ſon</hi> Iſaac, <hi>whom thou loueſt, &amp;c. Genſe.</hi> 22.2. <hi>Eſto domine,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>quia de filio commemor as pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem.</hi> Be it ſo Lord that thou putteſt the father in minde of his ſon.<note n="s" place="margin">Fulmen non minus terribile <hi>Abrahamo,</hi> quam ſi iubetur cor ſibi cruere, imo ſe cum vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſo mundo in infernum praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitare. <hi>Pareus in Gen. 22.</hi>
                  </note> This is one torture, to thinke, that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt now become his childes butcher.<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen</hi> vt ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>Sed addis chariſſimum, &amp;c.</hi> Thou addeſt thy deareſt, or onely ſonne, and not content with that, but ſayeſt alſo<note n="u" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>quem diligis,</hi> whom thou loueſt. It is likely that <hi>Abraham</hi> hauing beene ſo long without a ſonne, was well affected towards him now he had him, but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:26126:25"/>was this a fit time to put him in minde of his loue?<note n="v" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Sint et in hoc parenti triplicata ſupplicia.</hi> Let vs obſerue here three tortures to the fathers minde, as ſo many daggers at his heart. But vvhat neede was there after all this, to name <hi>Iſaac?</hi> did not the father know that this his ſonne, his <hi>deare ſonne, whom hee loued,</hi> was called <hi>Iſaac?</hi> yes, and he remembred the promiſe to,<note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 17.21.</note> in <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhall thy ſeed be called. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.21. yet God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beares not to name him, that ſo<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen</hi> in Geneſ. ho. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Commemoratio nominis,</hi> might be <hi>deſperatio promiſſionis:</hi> the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his name, might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation of the promiſe, by which he ſhould not looſe his childe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but his owne ſoule alſo, and not that alone, but the ſoules of all men in the world beſide: ſuch a triall neuer lay on any man before, nor neuer ſhall againe; and yet <hi>Abraham</hi> would haue done it.</p>
               <p>But if you marke it, there is no
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26126:25"/>compariſon betweene the loue of <hi>Abraham</hi> to God, and the loue of GOD to man. For what equality betweene <hi>Iſaac</hi> a young lad, and Chriſt the eternall ſonne of God? Againe <hi>Iſaac</hi> muſt haue dyed once, for he ought God a death,<note n="z" place="margin">Omnia quae de Chriſto legeris non neceſſitate, ſed ſponte facta reperies. <hi>Origen</hi> in Gen. hom. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> Chriſt had no ſuch neceſſitie, being debter to no man. <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſitting, bare a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wood on his necke; Chriſt walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carryed an heauy croſſe on his ſhoulders, and bare that which bare him, fainting vnder it, and dying vpon it. <hi>Iſaac</hi> had a Ramme ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed for him, held by the hornes in a buſh; Chriſt was the Ramme himſelfe, held by the hornes,<note n="a" place="margin">Quid eſt enim haerere cornibus, niſi crucifigi? <hi>Aug.</hi> in Pſal. <hi>30.</hi>
                  </note> whilſt hee was nayled to the Croſſe, and his head in the buſh, whilſt the buſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es were on his head, whilſt hee was crowned with thornes. Laſtly, <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhould haue ſuffred in a mountaine, where none ſhould haue ſeene him; it ſtood<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 22.4.</note> three dayes iourney off. Chriſt ſuffred afterward in the<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieronimus</hi> presbyter ſcripſit ab antiquis et ſenioribus <hi>Iudae is,</hi> ſe certiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſime cognouiſſe, quod ibi immola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſit <hi>Iſaac,</hi> vbi poſtea Chriſtus crucifixus ſit. <hi>Aug.</hi> de temper. ſer. <hi>71.</hi>
                  </note> ſame mountaine, as ſome thinke, or not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:26126:26"/>farre from it, as is moſt certaine, and was held in his ſuffrings three dayes and three nights together.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the loue of God to his Church exceedes the loue that is betweene the husband and the wife. For<note n="d" place="margin">Quis enim poteſt ſic ducere, vt moriatur pro ea quam vult ducere? Si enim mori pro ea qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vult ducere, volucrit, non crit qui ducat. Securus autem ille pro ſponſa mortuus eſt. quam reſurgens erat ducturus. <hi>Aug. in Pſ. 122.</hi>
                  </note> what man being to marry, would chuſe a deformed, blacke, and adulterous wife? Or hauing choſen ſuch a one in marriage, would loue her ſo much as to dye for her? Yet Chriſt hath done ſo for his Church his Church ſo adulterous, ſo defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Therefore hee is ſaid, when ſhe was<note n="e" place="margin">Ezek. 16.16.</note> polluted in her bloud<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to<note n="f" place="margin">Ib. verſ. 9.</note> waſh her with water, and annoint her with oyle. When ſhe was naked and bare, to<note n="g" place="margin">Ezek. 16.13.</note> decke her with broy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded worke of gold, ſiluer, and fine linnen. When ſhee was<note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. 16.8.</note> caſt out, to take her vp, and to enter into a couenant with her, and make her his owne. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8. Therefore, this his marriage with his Church, ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">Per nuptias Moyſi nuptiae <hi>verbi oſtende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur, et per Aethyopiſſam coniugem Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam.</hi> Irenae. lib. 4. cap 37.</note> 
                  <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> was like the marriage of <hi>Moyſes</hi> with the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26126:26"/>The one bride was as defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue in grace, as the other defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in nature. But Chriſt did more for his ſpouſe, then euer <hi>Moyſes</hi> could doe for his Bride, as <hi>Bernard</hi> notes,<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> dom. 1. poſt, Octa. Epiph. ſerm. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Moyſes Aethyopiſſam quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam duxit vxorem ſed eius non potuit mutare colorem, &amp;c. Moyſes</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a certaine blacke Ethyopian, but was not able to change her skinne from blacke to white; But Chriſt tooke to him a Spouſe that was farre more ignoble and filthy, and by waſhing her with his owne bloud, hath made her a chaſt Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to himſelfe, without ſpot or wrinckle.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it exceedes the loue that is betweene the body and the ſoule; betwixt which yet, there is ſo great loue, that the one grieues to part with the other: yea, euen in the moſt ſanctified men, there is a kinde of reluctation againſt death, the ſoule ſhrinkes at the bodies diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. For that which <hi>Ierome</hi> tells
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26126:27"/>of holy<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierm.</hi> in vita <hi>Hilarion,</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hilarion,</hi> ſaying to his ſoule thus, <hi>Egredere, quid times? egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere anima mea quid dubitas?</hi> Goe out my ſoule, goe out, what feareſt thou? what doubteſt thou? that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares a kinde of vnwillingneſſe which nature hath to come to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; and that death is,<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper Cant. ſer. 26.</note> as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> cals it, <hi>Horrendum diuortium;</hi> a moſt wofull ſeparation, not onely of the dead from the liuing, but of the dead from himſelfe. Yet Chriſt moſt willingly ſuffered this moſt grieuous partition and ſeparation of his body and ſoule aſunder, that hee might ioyne vs to God, that were ſeparate from him, and our ſelues to.</p>
               <p>Finally, what ſhall I ſay? ſo much was Chriſt tranſported beyond himſelfe, or (to ſpeake more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly) ſo much brought ſhort of himſelfe by loue, that he<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exinaniuit ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum.</hi> Phil. 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>emptied</hi> himſelfe of all reſpect, and made himſelfe as nothing at all. Euen hee which at firſt made all things of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:26126:27"/>nothing, did afterwards make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of himſelfe. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> cals loue<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nazian</hi> orat. 28. in <hi>Maxim.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>dulcem tyrannum,</hi> a ſweet ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. And<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper Cant. ſer. 64.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Triumphat de Deo amor,</hi> Loue triumphed ouer the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed. O ſtrange triumph! <hi>Quis triumphantis currus?</hi> What chariot had this Conquerour thus to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in? <hi>Sanè Crux,</hi> no other chariot but the Croſſe. Here Loue diſplayed his Banner, and hung vp his Scutcheon, a bleeding heart for our miſerie, vnfolded armes for our imbracing, a bended head to incline to vs, goared hands, head, feet, and ſide, to heale vs. So that if you aske what hard-heart bound Chriſt with fetters, ſcourged him with whips, crowned him with thornes, pierced him with ſpeare, and faſtned him with nayles, himſelfe will anſwere: <hi>Loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">
                        <hi>Borbon</hi> apud <hi>Ludouic. Granat.</hi> poſt. ill. To. 2.</note> Huc me ſydereo deſcendere fecit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympo,</l>
                  <l>Hic me crudeli vnluere fixit Amor.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:26126:28"/>Hither hath the tyrant Loue brought me downe to liue a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible &amp; a poore life: here hath the tyrant Loue faſtned mee to die an ignominious and a ſhamefull death.<note n="r" place="margin">D. <hi>Walſ.</hi> ſer. life and death of Chriſt.</note> 
                  <hi>O the loue it ſelfe of none, but of ſuch a one as is Loue it ſelfe!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wilt thou now be partaker of this great loue of GOD? Loue him and thou haſt it. For this is the rule of loue,<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſidor. Peluſ.</hi> lib. 2. epiſt. 148.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hee which deſires much loue, muſt himſelfe ſhew much loue.<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nazian.</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> enim quicquam ad amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ita firmum eſt, vt beneuolentia mutuo repenſa,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nazianzen;</hi> There is not any thing ſo ſtrong to draw affection of others, as when a man ſends forth good affections in himſelfe. Loue is the Load-ſtone of Loue. And therefore how can wee chuſe, vnleſſe we be more hard then iron, but wee muſt returne GOD ſome loue, that hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo much on vs firſt? <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:26126:28"/>
                  <note n="v" place="margin">Hieron. <hi>ad</hi> Celunt.</note> 
                  <hi>Nihil imperioſius charitate,</hi> Nothing is more imperious and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding then loue; it will force a man in whom it is, to make ſome teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of his good heart to GOD.<note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Charitas Dei vrget nos,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> The very loue of GOD conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p>O how ſhould wee abound in that vertue which <hi>Paul</hi> cals,<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 13.8.</note> 
                  <hi>The fulfilling of the Law, Rom.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Iames,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Iames 2.17.</note> 
                  <hi>The life of Faith, Iam.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Ierome,</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in Mat. hom. <hi>Hieron</hi> aduerſ. <hi>Iohan. Hieroſoly.</hi> ad <hi>Theop.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all vertues. Fulgentius,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Neceſt alia quae ſit vera ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia, &amp;c. <hi>Fulgent de praedeſt. lib 1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The whole wiſedome of the reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> And <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> ad <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtin.</hi> epiſt. 62.</note> 
                  <hi>A common debt, that can neuer be cleared, but that a man muſt be paying of it ſtill.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Semper debeo Charitatem</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>quae ſola etiam reddita, ſemper detinet debitorem.</hi> I am euer in debt with charitie (and therefore we are commanded to<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 13.8.</note> owe it) vvhich though I pay neuer ſo oft<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet I am commanded to owe it ſtill. But here is the comfort of it, the more a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:26126:29"/>man payes it to others, the more hee keepes it to himſelfe. For, as <hi>Tully</hi> could tell vs<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cic.</hi> pro <hi>Cn. Plane.</hi> vti habet <hi>A. Gell.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Diſſimilis eſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniae debitio &amp; gratiae:</hi> There is no likeneſſe betweene paying money and paying loue. For, a man cannot pay money vnleſſe hee haue it; and when hee hath paid it, hee hath it not: but a man cannot haue loue vnleſſe he pay it, and the more he payes it the more he hath it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let vs not be ſuch miſers and huckſters of our loue, as the men of the world be of their money, but let it flow forth amaine from vs vnto God.</p>
               <p>And as part of our loue, let vs ſpend ſome time in conſidering what CHRIST hath ſuffered for vs. Marke how the Church ſpeakes to each faithfull ſoule, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.11.<note n="f" place="margin">Cant. 3.11</note> 
                  <hi>Come forth yee daughters of Zion, behold your King Solomon, with the Crowne wherewith his mother crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him in the day of his marriage, in the day of the gladnes of his heart.</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:26126:29"/>That is, O yee faithfull ſoules, daughters of your Mother the Church, <hi>Come forth,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> in Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha. ſer. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Egredimini de ſenſu carnis ad intellectum mentis:</hi> Come forth out of the ſenſe of the fleſh, to the vnderſtanding of the minde: Come I ſay, a little out of your ſelues, and by holy medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Behold your King Solomon,</hi> your true<note n="h" place="margin">Eph. 2.14.</note> peace-maker, and your King to, Chriſt Ieſus: who,<note n="i" place="margin">Licet enim reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eius non ſit de hoc mundo, tamen rex eſt in hoc mundo. <hi>Bern. vt ſupra.</hi>
                  </note> though his kingdome be not of this world, yet is a King euen in this world, <hi>With the Crowne wherewith his mother crowned him,</hi> that is, with the crowne of thornes vpon his head, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with his mother the Synagogue,<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> paru. ſer. ſer. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Quae ei ſe non matrem exhibuit, ſed nouercam,</hi> which proued not her ſelfe to him a kinde mother, but a cruell ſtepdame: <hi>Crowned him,</hi> that is,<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertul.</hi> de co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. milit.</note> 
                  <hi>faedauit, &amp; lancinauit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian,</hi> gaſhed him, and goared him, <hi>In the day of his marriage,</hi> that is, in the day of his paſſion vpon the Croſſe, when hee was marryed to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:26126:30"/>his Church built out of his ſide, as <hi>Adam</hi> to his <hi>Eue</hi> created of his rib. <hi>In the day of the gladneſſe of his heart,</hi> that is, in the very ſeaſon of his ſuffering, which was as ioyfull to him, as a geniall and nupriall day to a Bridegrome. Come forth I ſay, ſee him, conſider of him, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on him,<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard.</hi> in feſto omn. Sanct. ſer. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Pudeat ſub ſpinato capite membrum fieri delicatum;</hi> and let it ſhame you vnder an head ſo crowned with thornes, to be as members of wanton and delicate niceneſſe.</p>
               <p>The ſame thing which the Church deſires of her members, himſelfe deſires of his Church,<note n="n" place="margin">Cant. 8.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Set me as a ſeale on thine heart, and as a ſignet on thine arme, Cant.</hi> 8.6. words by ſome attributed to the Church, but by the<note n="o" place="margin">Ambroſe. Gregory. Aponius. Caſſiodor. Beda. Bernard. <hi>Vide etiam</hi> Tuccium. Sotto maio. Ghiſterium, <hi>&amp; alios ad loc.</hi>
                  </note> Fathers applyed to CHRIST, wherein hee deſires her continually to remember him. As if hee had ſaid: My deareſt, though I am now going from thee for a time, yet forget mee not, but
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:26126:30"/>as a louing wife, frames the Image of her deare husband in her heart; and as a<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tucci. Lucenſ.</hi> annot. <hi>Cincin.</hi> pag. 378.</note> longing woman imprints the forme of the thing which ſhee longs for on the childe in her wombe; ſo ſet me as a ſeale on thy ſoule, thinke on me, delight in me, And as that famous<note n="q" place="margin">Id. ib.</note> 
                  <hi>Artemiſia</hi> ſo much affected her dead husband <hi>Mauſolus,</hi> that ſhee tooke the dead aſhes of his vrne, and mingled them with her drinke, and ſo intombed his dead carke is within her liuing body; ſo doe thou my Spouſe, haue mee euer within thee, eate me and drinke me in the Sacrament, let me be in <hi>thine heart,</hi> and on <hi>thine arme,</hi> in thy intention, in thy operation, within thee, without thee, euery where, and at all times, let mee be loued and thought on, on earth, as I am care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of thee in heauen. Let vs then, ô let vs fulfill his deſire now, that hee may accompliſh all our deſires hereafter. And ſo much of this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:26126:31"/>
               <head>My Doue.</head>
               <p>THAT the <hi>Doue</hi> ſignifies the Church, beſide the iudgement of wiſe <hi>Eſdras</hi> ſaying,<note n="r" place="margin">2 Eſdr. 5.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Of all the fowles that are created thou haſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thee one Doue,</hi> 2 <hi>Eſdr.</hi> 5.26. and beſides the teſtimonie of Chriſt himſelfe, calling her his Doue,<note n="s" place="margin">Cant. 2.10. &amp; Cant. 2.14. &amp; Cant. 5.2. &amp; Cant. 6.8.</note> foure times at leaſt in this booke: the due reſemblance which that creature hath with Chriſts Spouſe, doth moſt ſufficiently declare. Due reſemblance two manner of wayes, in her ſeuerall members of body, and her naturall practiſe of life.</p>
               <p>For her members: in at leaſt ſixe of them ſhe ſweetly reſembles the Church. Beginne we with her Bill, which is all the weapon that ſhee hath;<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper Cant. ſerm. 59.</note> 
                  <hi>Roſtro non loedit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> ſhee hurts no body with it. With other Birds the Bill is guiltie of two horrible crimes, capine and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:26126:31"/>crueltie: for with the Kyte,<note n="v" place="margin">
                     <hi>Alciat.</hi> embl. 128.</note> 
                  <hi>roſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> is <hi>raſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> her beake a rake to ſcratch all ſtore of prouiſion together: whereupon ſhee is made the<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pierius</hi> lib. 17.</note> hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphicke of a rauenous Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner. With Crowes and Rauens, the <hi>beake</hi> is a <hi>bodkin,</hi> to picke out the eyes of young Lambes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther harmleſſe Creatures. But with the Doue it is quite contrary; her weapon harmes not,<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr.</hi> de vnita. Eccleſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Non morſibus ſaeuum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cyprian</hi>) it bites not to hurt: but which is more, it is the member of true concord, and the inſtrument of chaſte loue: for, Doues wooe by the Bill; whence comes the phraſe in <hi>Seneca,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Senes.</hi> epiſt. 114.</note> 
                  <hi>colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bari labris,</hi> to giue mutuall kiſſes each to other. Thus fares it vvith the Church; hurt ſhee doth none, euen in her greateſt ſtrength.<note n="z" place="margin">Iſay 11.9.</note> 
                  <hi>None hurts nor deſtroyes in all mine holy Mountaine,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>Iſay</hi> 11.9. Hurts not, but which is more, with her weapons doe good,<note n="a" place="margin">Iſay. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Turnes Swords into Mattockes, and Speares
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:26126:32"/>into Sythes,</hi> making weapons of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie to be inſtruments of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
               <p>Paſſe wee forth from her Bill to her voyce, becauſe her voyce paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth forth from her Bill. It is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from the voyce of all Birds. For all other Birds are ſaid <hi>Canere,</hi> to ſing, ſhe<note n="b" place="margin">Nec gemere atreaceſſabit turtur ab vlmo. <hi>Virg.</hi> Et coſius turtur at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> columba ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt. <hi>Ouid.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>gemere,</hi> to mourne: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the voyce of mourning is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the voyce of Doues,<note n="c" place="margin">Nah. 2.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Nahum</hi> 2.7. <hi>Huzzah ſhall be led away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and her maides ſhall leade her as with the voyce of Doues.</hi> Such is the voyce of the Church, euen a voyce of mourning and ſad lamenting. Hence Chriſt,<note n="d" place="margin">Cant. 2.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Vox Turturis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita eſt in terra noſtra, Can.</hi> 2.12. The voyce of the Turtle is heard in our Land; which is, when<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> wee, <hi>which haue the firſt fruits of the Spirit, doe mourne in our ſelues, waiting for the Adoption, euen the redemption of our body, Rom.</hi> 8.23. Thus<note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 38.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Hezekiah</hi> of himſelfe; <hi>I did mourne as a Doue, Iſa.</hi> 38.14. Thus<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 59.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> of himſelfe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:26126:32"/>and others, <hi>We all mourne like doues, Iſa.</hi> 59.11.</p>
               <p>And as God commanded in the Law, to offer<note n="h" place="margin">Luc. 2.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Par turturum,</hi> a paire of Turtles,<note n="i" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; duos pullos columbinos,</hi> two yong Pigions: ſo in the Goſpell, the righteous doe<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonau.</hi> in Luc. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>geminare gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> mourne doubly. Firſt, for their owne ſinnes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.6.<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>I faint in my mourning, euery night waſh I my bed and water my couch with my teares.</hi> And this muſt be done, becauſe it is not enough, ſaith<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſelm.</hi> lib. de ſimil. cap. 102.</note> 
                  <hi>Anſelme, Vt ſe cognoſcat quis peccatorem, niſi inde habeat &amp; dolorem;</hi> for a man to know himſelfe a ſinner, vnleſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hee ſhew himſelfe to be a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower. But if hee grieue for his ſin, then his ſin ſhall neuer grieue him.<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in Mat. hom. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Sicut euim poſt vehementes imbres, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) Euen as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter moſt vehement ſtormes the Sunne ſhines moſt faire; <hi>Ita etiam lachrymarum plunias ſerenitas mentis ſequitur;</hi> Euen ſo after bitter teares there followes a pleaſant calme, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:26126:33"/>an heauenly Sun-ſhine in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for the ſinnes of other men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.136.<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 119.136</note> 
                  <hi>Mine eyes guſh out with water, becauſe men keepe not thy Law.</hi> To which purpoſe ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ad <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſt.</hi> epiſt. 145.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine, Pia eſt iſta triſtitia, &amp; ſi dici poteſt, beata miſeria, vitijs aliorum tribulari, non implicari, moe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere, non harere, &amp;c.</hi> That is a godly ſorrow, and if I may ſo ſay, a bleſſed miſery, for a man to be partaker of ſorrow for another mans ſinne, not to partake of the ſinne it ſelfe; to ioyne in mourning for it, not in committing of it. And this is not one of the leaſt perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which a good man finds in this world; Becauſe,<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> vt ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>Coram pio, viuens impie, etſi non obligat conſentientem, cruciat ſentientem:</hi> Whileſt the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man liues ill before the good mans face, though the good mans hand toucheth not the ſin, yet the ſin toucheth the good mans heart; and anothers committing of it goes
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:26126:33"/>neare to him that is farre from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of it himſelfe. Therefore<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr.</hi> ad lapſos §. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> writes thus to them that fell in time of perſecution; <hi>Doleo fratres, doleo, nec mihi ad leniendos dolores integritas propria, &amp; ſanitas priuata blanditur:</hi> O my brethren, weepe I muſt with you, and for you: for to ſtay my griefe is neither able the ſincerity of my ſoule, nor ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my body. And<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard.</hi> de conſid lib.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> to <hi>Eugenius; ſi doles condoleo, ſi non doles doleo:</hi> If thou be ſory I am ſory with thee, if thou be not ſory I am ſory for thee.</p>
               <p>See we now her Eyes: and theſe are both attentiue againſt euill, and intentiue toward good. Attentiue againſt euill;<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig.</hi> in Leuit. hom. 3. Idem &amp; <hi>Greg.</hi> in Cant. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Ferunt Columbas cum ad aquas venerint, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Origen,</hi> The report is that the Doue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the water, eſpies there the ſhadow of her enemy the Hawke, and ſo, <hi>Oculorum perſpicacia,</hi> by the quicke ſight of her eye auoids the danger. So, the Church comming
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:26126:34"/>to the Scripture, which is, the<note n="v" place="margin">Cant. 4.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Fountaine of the gardens, the Well of liuing waters, and the Springs of Lebanon, Cant.</hi> 4.15. findes there the traines of her arch-enemie the Diuell, and accordingly eſcapes them. Happy man that is euer ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the banckes of theſe waters, euer hauing his eyes fixed in this cleare fountaine, which may ſerue him as a glaſſe to ſee his faults and his fals, both the ſinne of his ſoule, and the puniſhment of his ſinne, and ſo eſchew the perill. The Lauer that was ſet vp by <hi>Moyſes</hi> in the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, was made of the peoples Glaſſes,<note n="u" place="margin">Exod. 38.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 38.8. ſo as that which at firſt ſhewed them their blemiſhes, did afterwards afford them water to waſh them off. Such a Lauer is the Scripture, that when it hath once made the blemiſh ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, yeelds alſo matter to purge vs from it. Here then let vs continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally fixe our eyes, that it may be ſaid of each Chriſtian, as the Church
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:26126:34"/>ſaith of Chriſt. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.12.<note n="x" place="margin">Cant. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>His eyes are like the Doues vpon the riuers of waters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, the Doues eyes are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue to her good. For ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they are caſt vpward, and fixed toward heauen: there being this difference between the Doue and the Swine, hee cloaſeth his eyes with the vpper lid, and ſo is blinde toward heauen; ſhee with the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lid, and ſo is blinde toward earth. And when ſhe drinkes at the brooke, ſhe caſts vp a looke to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in token of thankfulneſſe for the ſame. Such eyes hath the Church.<note n="y" place="margin">Cant. 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Oculi tui columbarum,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, thine eyes are like the Doues. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.14. Like the Doues,<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> ſup. cant. ſerm. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>id eſt, ſpirituales<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eyes. Not deceiued with the faire ſhewes of temporall vanities, but delighted with the glorious beauty of celeſtiall verities, ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Theod.</hi> ad loc.</note> 
                  <hi>Theodoret.</hi> Theſe eyes<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> in ſent.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith are two, <hi>Rerum labentium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratio,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26126:35"/>&amp;c. Coeleſtis patriae digna aeſtimatio.</hi> One, a due conſideration of the fickleneſſe of our earthly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle; The other, a worthy va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luation of the permanency of our heauenly country. With this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eye, ſhee hath wounded Chriſts heart. <hi>Can.</hi> 4.9.<note n="c" place="margin">Cant. 4.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt wounded mine heart with one of thine eyes, and a chaine of thy necke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let vs then, O let vs giue our ſelues to meditation, and often ſtudy of heauenly things. For, ſo much as wee ſee by diuine meditation, ſo much wee ſee indeede.<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Periand.</hi> in Auſonio.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith <hi>Periander. Meditation is all in all</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in ſpeculo peccatoris.</note> 
                  <hi>Meditatio, mentis ditatio,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> Meditation is the inriching of the minde.<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> de conſider. lib. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Haec men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem purificat, regit affectus, dirigit actus, &amp;c.</hi> This, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the minde, rules the affections, gouernes the actions, frames the manners, orders the life. And hee which ſpends not ſome part of his life this quiet way, caſteth his whole
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:26126:35"/>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Tam pio, tam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vtili conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis otio, nulla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vita dare operam nonne vitam perdere eſt? Bern. <hi>vtſup.</hi>
                  </note> life quite away. No meruaile then, if there bee ſo many poore ſoules in the world, ſeeing they regard not to inrich themſelues with contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation. No meruaile, if ſo many looſe their liues in buſineſſe, and toyles of things earthly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeeing they regard not to ſpend their liues in meditation, and ſtudy of things hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly.</p>
               <p>Next followes her Necke: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable two wayes: For ſtrength, for beautie. For ſtrength, for if there be any force in her bill, either for defence, or offence, it comes from her necke. For beautie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, that, of all parts of her body caſts out the moſt radiant hew, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Nero</hi> his verſe in <hi>Seneca.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Senec. <hi>nat. queſt. lib. 1.</hi> Columbae dictae eo quod eorum colla ad ſingulas conuerſiones colorem mutent. Iſid. <hi>orig. lib. 12. cap. 7.</hi>
                  </note> Colla Cytheriacae ſplendent agita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a columbae.</q>
               <p>The necke of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> doues ſhines bright when it moues. Thus the Churches necke is moſt ſtrong, moſt comely. Wherevpon he ſaith <hi rend="sup">i</hi> 
                  <hi>Thy necke is like a tower of Iuory.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:26126:36"/>Cant.</hi> 7.4.<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lyra</hi> ad loc. Cant. 7.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Firmum,</hi> or, <hi>rectum ad modum turris, album ad modum ebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lyra.</hi> Strong, or ſtraight after the manner of a tower, white or beauteous after the manner of iuory.</p>
               <p>Now the necke of the Church, through which the voyce paſſeth out, and the meate paſſeth in, and by whom the body and head are coupled together, are the<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Per collum Spouſae praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catores Sanctae Eccleſiae deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantur. Greg.</hi> in Cant. 1. Aponius. in Cant. 7. Serab. in gloſſ. ordinar. ad Cant. 7. etalij.</note> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Preachers of Gods word. They are the voyce both of head and body. Of the head Chriſt, when they preach his word to the Church Of the body the Church, when they put vp her prayers to Chriſt. They are the throate,<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſſiod.</hi> in Cant. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>quia accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos verbi dei cibos nutriendo corpori tranſmittunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Caſsiodore,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they receiue the meate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction firſt of all themſelues, and then conuay it into the bowels of others. Theſe are beautifull, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they adorne others with wholeſome doctrine; and ſtrong,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:26126:36"/>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Strab.</hi> ad loc.</note> 
                  <hi>quia exemplo, vitae, alios muniunt,</hi> becauſe they confirme and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then others by good example.</p>
               <p>The very ſame thing is ſignified by her Wings: which are not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, but rare, like the wings of a Phoenix. This Doue, ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 68.13.</note> 
                  <hi>is couered with ſiluer wings, and her feathers like gold. Pſal.</hi> 68.13. Where by the way, noate, that in <hi>Paleſtina,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sebaſt. Barrad</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. Eu. to. 2. lib. 1. cap. 15.</note> as I reade, were faire large white doues, whoſe feathers toward their backe looked yealowiſh, and ſo as white, had the colour of ſiluer, and as yealowiſh, the colour of gold. For which goodlineſſe, in part, they of Aſſyria worſhipped the doue, as the Poet inſinuates:</p>
               <q>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tibull.</hi> eleg. 7. lib. 1.</note> Alba Palaeſtino ſancto columba Syro.</q>
               <p>Now,<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>Strab.</hi> in gloſſ. ord. ad Pſal. 67.</note> 
                  <hi>alae columbae, doctores eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae</hi> ſaith one. The doues ſiluered fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are the Churches ſiluer head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fathers. For as the wings of a doue beare vp the whole bulk of her body, from the earth into the aire; ſo the Paſtors and Teachers of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:26126:37"/>Church beare vp the whole body thereof, from earthly conceits to heauenly meditations: truely there fore called<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 68.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Pennae argentatae,</hi> Pennes and that of ſiluer. Pennes,<note n="v" place="margin">Pſal. 45.2.</note> becauſe they declare the minde of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.2. <hi>My tongue is the pen of a ready writer.</hi> Siluer pennes,<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in Pſal. 67.</note> 
                  <hi>Quia diuinis eloquijs eruditi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> becauſe they ſhine with the brightnes of Gods word, which is<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal 12.7.</note> as ſiluer tryed ſeauen times in the fire. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.6. With the helpe of theſe wings the doue of Chriſts Church flyes the net of the fowler, and mounts vp to her neaſt in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Therefore when the Dragon, the Diuell, would haue deuoured the woman, the Church,<note n="y" place="margin">Reu. 12.14.</note> wings were giuen her, Paſtors beſtowed on her, to carry her into a place of reſt and ſecurity. <hi>Reu.</hi> 12.14.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, let theſe ſiluer wings of the doue, be like the golden wings of the <hi>Seraphins:</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">2 Chro. 3.11.</note> as theſe were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually extended out in the top of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:26126:37"/>the Temple: ſo let the other be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſtretched out in the middeſt of the Church. And as the ſeraphins wings were ſo ordered that one touched another, ſo let the paſtors of the Church be ſo animated that one ſecond another. To conclude, let each wing of the Church bee as the<note n="a" place="margin">Ezek. 1.34.</note> wings of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> beaſts, <hi>which ſent out from them the voyce of ſpeach, like the voyce of the Almighty. Ezek.</hi> 1.24. Let them preach diligently. For a dumbe Miniſter is as a clipt wing, which lets the body fall, when hee ſhould make it flye. Such were the falſe Prophets among the Iewes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 2.34.<note n="b" place="margin">Ierem. 2.34.</note> 
                  <hi>In thy wings is found the blood of the ſoules of the poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents.</hi> And ſuch is euery laſie Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, who being Gods meſſenger, yet ſaith nothing for him, but liues as it were poſſeſſed with a dumbe Diuell. Of euery ſuch, a man may ſay, as <hi>Bleſenſis</hi> ſaid of <hi>Richard</hi> of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie</hi> the Popes Legate,<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bleſenſ.</hi> ad Richar. Cant. Epi. 5.</note> Hee is <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus, potius quam legatus.</hi> Not an
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:26126:38"/>eloquent embaſſador, but a tongue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyed mumbler.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, the Doue hath no gall. Such is the common iudgement of all men: vpon the truth of it I will not ſtand, but take it as I finde it; yet all auncient writers, ſaith <hi>Pierius,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pierius</hi> hieroglyp. lib. 22.</note> are of opinion that ſhe hath none; or if any, <hi>in vropygio eſſe tradunt,</hi> they thinke it to bee in the lower part of her chine: but Diuines, I am ſure are wholly this way, that ſhee wants it.<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron.</hi> in Pſal. 54.</note> 
                  <hi>Sine felle, &amp; a malitia fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis alienum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierome:</hi> without gall, or any bitterneſſe of malice.<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprian.</hi> de vnitat. Eccleſ. Item <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in Mat. hom. 12. et in Geneſ. hom. 26. et <hi>Bed.</hi> commen. in Mar. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Non felle amarum, non morſibus ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian,</hi> Not bitter in gall nor violent in biting.</p>
               <p>Which made the Graecians,<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pierius</hi> hierog. lib. 22.</note> when they went about to expreſſe the image of meekeneſſe, to name <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the quiet &amp; ſtil doue, and to ſay of a moſt patient man,<note n="h" place="margin">Columbae manſuetior.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the ſame ſenſe. And this, ſome thinke vvas the reaſon, why <hi>Dauid</hi> being much
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:26126:38"/>diſquieted in minde about the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of ſome of his friends in <hi>Sauls</hi> court, cryed out,<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 55.6.</note> 
                  <hi>O that I had wings like a Doue, for then would I flie away, and be at reſt.</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nazianz.</hi> orat. in Sanct. baptiſ. et Nicet. Scholi. ibidem.</note> Not wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Eagles vvings vvhich are more lofty, nor for Hawkes wings which are more liuely, becauſe, theſe indeed vvould carry a man away, but not bring him to reſt, quietneſſe being purchaſed, not ſo much by departing from our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye that is about vs, as by fleeing from the enimitie that is within vs.</p>
               <p>Such a Doue is the Church. As the one hath not the bitterneſſe of gall, no more hath the other the gall of bitterneſſe.<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprian</hi> de vnitat. Eccl.</note> 
                  <hi>In domo dei, in Eccleſia Chriſti, vnanimes habitant,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian, concordes et ſimplices perſeuerant.</hi> In Gods houſe, which is Chriſtes Church, men are of one minde, holding out in ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city and concord. Their guide is the ſpirit of God,<note n="m" place="margin">Wiſd. 8.16.</note> 
                  <hi>whoſe company hath no bitterneſſe, nor fellowſhip
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:26126:39"/>tediouſneſſe.</hi> §ap. 8.16. As for the viperous brood of malignant miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants, that breath out nothing but treacherous concluſions, and ſubuerting ſtratagems, they are of the ſinagogue of Satan, and of the faction of Antichriſt.<note n="n" place="margin">Deut. 32.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Their vine is of the vine of Sodome, and of the vines of Gomorrhah, their grapes are grapes of gall; their cluſters be bitter. Their wine is of the poyſon of Dragons, and the cruell gall of Aſpes, Deut.</hi> 32.32, Such ſauour not of <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> but of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that hee was fallen,<note n="o" place="margin">Act. 8.23.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.23. Into the gall of bitterneſſe, and bond of iniquitie.</p>
               <p>Wherefore let vs follow Chriſts Doue in ſimplicitie, not Satans Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in ſubtiltie. In our Baptiſme GOD ſends his Doue, that is, his ſpirit to vs; as the Doue came downe at the baptiſme of CHRIST. Now then, ſaith<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſo.</hi> in Mat. hom. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſoſtome, Quam veuiam sperare poterimus, ſi ad ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentem
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:26126:39"/>currimus poſt Columbam?</hi> What pardon can wee hope for, if leauing the innocency of Doues, we runne to borrow poyſon of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent? And thus you ſee, how the Doue reſembles the Church in the ſeuerall parts of her body. See it now in the practiſe of her life.</p>
               <p>The practiſe of her life is ſute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the properties of her nature; and her properties of nature reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Church diuers wayes. Firſt, in reſpect of matrimoniall fidelitie. Wherein of all Doues the Turtle is moſt excellent.<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper Cant. ſerm. 59.</note> 
                  <hi>Compare vno con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenta eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard, quo amiſſo, alterum iam non admittit.</hi> She con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents her ſelfe with one mate, who being loſt, ſhee reſts continually a widow. And for more credence herein,<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> vt ſup.</note> you may ſee her, <hi>ſanctae vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duitatis opus ſtrenue, &amp; infatigabiliter exequentem,</hi> euery where executing and performing the office of holy widdowhood ſtoutly and reſolutly: Euery where alone, euery where
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:26126:40"/>mourning, at no time ſitting on greene boughes, but on the withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red tops of trees, or on the houſe,<note n="s" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irentia vt virulenta fugit.</hi> Such pleaſant manſions ſhe hates as poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Such a faithfull doue is the Church, who being in this life a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour of holy widowhood ſets her heart wholly on Chriſt her dead husband, mournes after him, aſpires to him, and takes delight in nothing beſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in reſpect of her man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of building. For the doue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly makes her neſt in a ſtrong and ſure place, and therefore chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the holes of a rocke, or ſome hollow receptacle of a Church or houſe. Thus builds Chirſts Spouſe. <hi>Cant.</hi> 214.<note n="t" place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Columba mea in forami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus petrae,</hi> My doue that art in the holes of the rocke, &amp;c. Now the generall opinion of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is, that<note n="v" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Michael. Ghiſlerium ad locum. Cant. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>vulnera Chriſti</hi> are <hi>foramina petrae,</hi> the wounds of Chriſt the holes of the rocke. In them
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:26126:40"/>the Church builds her defence, they are meritorious, with them ſhe fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers her neaſt, they are plentious. Shee neyther builds with the ſticks of mans free-will, nor daubes with the dirt of mans good deſerts, nor couers with the moſſe of his ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined Supererogations: but goes into the rocke as ſhe findes it open, and there receiues reſt and ſecuritie againſt all feares.<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> ſup. Cant-ſerm. 61.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid non boni in petra?</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) what good can I not hope for in the rocke? <hi>In petra exaltatus, in petra ſecurus, in petra firmiter ſto:</hi> In the rocke I am exalted and lifted towards heauen, in the rocke ſecured and freed from earth, in the rocke I ſtand firmely; <hi>ſecurus ab hoſte, fortis a caſu;</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fright of foe, or feare of falling.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of faecunditie or fruitfulneſſe:<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſt.</hi> hiſt. anim. lib. 5. cap. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that the Doue breedes tenne times, or eleuen times in the yeere: yea, which is ſtrange, by<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin.</hi> nat. hiſt. lib. 10. cap. 58.</note> 
                  <hi>Plinies</hi> acount, ſhee breedes thirteene or foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:26126:41"/>times in the yeer. For in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time, within two moneths ſhee brings forth three paire, in ſo much as in the ſame neaſt, you may ſee diuers ſorts of young ones, <hi>alios pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolantes, alios erumpentes,</hi> ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to flye, ſome but breaking the ſhell. Hence, as ſome thinke, ſhe is call,<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Scalig. Pierius</hi> &amp; alij.</note> 
                  <hi>Columba, quia colit lumbos ſaepe parturiendo:</hi> for her often bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Such a carefull breeder is the Church, who brings forth children in abundance,<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg. Moral.</hi> lib. 19.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Et creſcentes filios</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) <hi>quaſi plumeſcentes pullos, charitatis gremio fonet, &amp;c.</hi> and keepes her new borne babes in Chriſt, like young Pigeons in the boſome of Charitie, as it were in a ſafe neſt till by Faith they be able to flye vp to God in heauen. Thus was it propheſied to this Bride;<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 45.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.17. <hi>In ſtead of thy Fathers thou ſhalt haue children, whom thou maiſt make Princes in all lands.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prophet in admiration ſaith;<note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 49.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Lift vp thine eyes round about,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:26126:41"/>and behold all theſe gather themſelues together, and come to thee. As I liue ſaith the Lord, thou ſhalt put them all vpon thee as a garment, and gird thy ſelfe with them as a Bride. Behold, I will lift vp mine hands to the Gentiles, and ſet vp my Standard to the people, and they ſhall bring thy Sonnes in their armes, and thy daughters ſhall be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed vpon their ſhoulders, Iſa.</hi> 49.18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thus much for the third Epithet, <hi>My Doue:</hi> Come we to the fourth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>My Vndefiled.</head>
               <p>THE word ſignifies<note n="d" place="margin">Immaculata.</note> 
                  <hi>without ſpot,</hi> and by conſequence <hi>pitre.</hi> This puritie of the Church is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde: Of imputation, of action: that, purity before God; this, before men. All her puritie is imputed, whereof ſome ſhee hath to iuſtifie, and ſome to ſanctifie.<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 45.13.</note> 
                  <hi>The Kings Daughter is all glorious within,</hi> her
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:26126:42"/>ſoule is precious through imputed righteouſneſſe; and yet, <hi>her cloathing is of wrought gold:</hi> her life is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous with outward holineſſe.</p>
               <p>All her pureneſſe before God is giuen vnto her of God. He it is that hath made her,<note n="f" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.27.</note> 
                  <hi>a chaſte virgin, not hauing ſpot or wrinckle, or any ſuch thing, Epheſ.</hi> 5.27. And this he hath done, by hiding her euill with the garment of his goodneſſe. For, as in himſelfe hee couered the diuine vertue with the vaile of our fleſh; ſo in vs he couers the humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie with the grace of his ſpirit. Whereupon ſhee ſings.<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 61.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee hath cloathed me with the garment of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and couered me with the roabe of righteouſneſſe. Iſa.</hi> 61.10. If any man ſay, Chriſts garment is his owne,<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper. Cant. ſer. 61.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> tels vs, <hi>Non eſt breue pallium, quod non poſſit operire duos,</hi> It is not ſo ſhort a cloake, but it may couer him and the Church to.</p>
               <p>And after Chriſt hath cloathed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:26126:42"/>her with his righteouſneſſe, ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files herſelfe no more with any old pollutions, but ſhines forth in the midſt of the darkneſſe of impietie, with the heauenly workes of true Chriſtianitie.<note n="i" place="margin">Cant. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Like the Lilly among the Thornes, ſo is my Loue among the Daughters, Cant.</hi> 2.2. And hence it is, that CHRIST himſelfe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth of her,<note n="k" place="margin">Cant. 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou art all fayre, my Loue, thou art all fayre, and there is no ſpot in thee, Cant.</hi> 4.7.</p>
               <p>But here take heede of an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of too much perfection, and too much puritie: the one hatched by the Fryers of <hi>Rome,</hi> the other by the Brethren of <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> For, they arrogate to the Church the greateſt height of perfection; theſe reiect from the Church the leaſt blemiſh of infirmitie. The firſt, an error of preſumptuous pride; the ſecond a conceit of prepoſterous zeale.</p>
               <p>That they of <hi>Rome</hi> hold, that<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22. quae. 184. a. 2.</note> perfection may be attained in this
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:26126:43"/>life, it is euident by their writings: and that not onely,<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar.</hi> de mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nac. lib. 2. cap. 2. Item <hi>Aquin.</hi> p. 22. quae. 184.2.6.</note> Monkes be in a ſtate of perfection <hi>adipiſcendae,</hi> to be attained vnto; Biſhops and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates in a ſtate of perfection, <hi>adeptae,</hi> attained already; and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that their Church cannot erre: but that alſo all other men, which are regenerate, are perfect, we haue their<note n="n" place="margin">Concil. Trid. Seſſ. 5. §. 5.</note> Councell auerring the point, <hi>In renatis nihil odit Deus,</hi> God hates nothing in the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. Now if God hate nothing in them, then haue they no ſinne, and to haue no ſinne is the greateſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection that can be.</p>
               <p>Againe, they of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> dreame of too much puritie of a Church, and therefore they ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelues from the true ſpouſe of Chriſt, becauſe of ſome preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded blemiſhes, and frame to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a <hi>Donatiſticall</hi> conuenticle; chuſing for the loue of an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned puritie, to become obſtinate and vaine-glorious Puritanes. But
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:26126:43"/>alas what comes of it? whileſt they would be the onely Church, they become indeede no Church.<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Petrus Bleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nſ.</hi> epiſt. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam inſipientiam ſimulando ſapiunt:</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>quidam nimis ſapiendo deſipiunt:</hi> Some men by the ſhew of folly are wiſe; and others againe by ſhewing their wiſedome become fooles. And what elſe doe theſe men by all their endeuours, but bewray their owne folly, whileſt they make of a remedy to vs, a diſeaſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? For our part, wee know the difference betweene the Church mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant, and the Church triumphant,<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ad <hi>Glor.</hi> epiſt. 162.</note> 
                  <hi>Illa in terris non amittit niſi malos, haec in coelum non admittit niſi bonos:</hi> The one looſeth none but bad men from her on earth, the other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues none but good men to her in heauen. The Church militant may haue her imperfections, but muſt not therefore be forſaken. It is her owne requeſt,<note n="q" place="margin">Cant. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Nolite conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derare me quod fuſca ſim, Cant.</hi> 1.6. Eſteeme mee not ſo much for
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:26126:44"/>my brownneſſe, as for my ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And therefore for our part, wee had rather be of the browne Church, then of <hi>Brownes</hi> Church; rather defiled in ſomething as wee ſtand, then filed away to nothing as they be; their reformation being like childrens pilling of an Onion, pilling alway till all be pilled away.</p>
               <p>Leauing therefore both theſe, let vs goe the middle way, and that we may haue an vndefiled Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, let vs ſtriue to haue an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled conuerſation. For our Church is not ſtained with the lies of her foes, but with the liues of her friends,<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper Cant. ſer. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Omnes amici, inimici,</hi> and, <hi>neceſſarij, aduerſarij;</hi> They are her friends that moſt fight againſt her, and her mothers ſonnes that are moſt<note n="s" place="margin">Cant. 1.5.</note> angry at her, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.5. Shee may ſay with <hi>Dauid</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 51.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Peccatum meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contra me ſemper.</hi> It is my ſinne, my ſinne that hurts mee.<note n="v" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> Dom. adu. ſer. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, morbus animae, &amp; corruptio mentis.</hi> Sinne it is, that is the ſoules
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:26126:44"/>ſore, and the minds miſery. And therefore God complaines of his Church,<note n="v" place="margin">Iſa. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>From the ſole of the foote to the crowne of the head, there is no ſoundneſſe, but wounds of ſwelling, and ſores of corruption.</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Bern.</note> 
                  <hi>Nulla ſanitas, quia nulla ſanctitas,</hi> No vvholeneſſe, becauſe no holineſſe.</p>
               <p>Couetouſneſſe is like a thirſty dropſie. For euen as men ſicke of an hydropicall diſeaſe,<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> in Matth. hom. <hi>64.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>non ſolum non extingunt ardorem potu, verum etiam incendunt,</hi> ſayth <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> by drinking are ſo farre from alay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their heate, that the more they drinke, the more they may. Euen ſo, ſuch as are ſicke of Couetouſnes, the more they get, the more they thirſt for, and neuer leaue ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, till<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Leo</hi> de iciun. dec. menſ. Serm. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Foenus pecuniae</hi> proues <hi>funus animae,</hi> as <hi>Leo</hi> ſpeakes, the birth of money proues the death of man.</p>
               <p>Enuy is a ranckling ſtripe in the ſoule. And therefore it is called<note n="a" place="margin">Lyra <hi>in Iſa.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Liuor,</hi> becauſe the enuious man doth continually beate himſelfe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:26126:45"/>blacke and blew vvith ſpight, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> truely,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr.</hi> de zelo &amp; liuore.</note> 
                  <hi>Dum ab inuidis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor nunquaem exponitur, die bus ac no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctibus pectus obſeſſum ſine intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one laniatur.</hi> Whileſt enuious men continually pine at other mens hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, they doe day and night but gaſh and wound their owne heart.</p>
               <p>Pride is a ſwelling tumour: for, as a noxious and noyſome humour, being met together in the fleſh, makes the body ſwell: ſo pride, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſoule, makes the heart to ſwell. Hence comes high thoughts in the minde, big lookes in the face, great words in the mouth, as ſo many outward Symptomes of that inward diſeaſe. Hence exoticke fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions in the apparrell, fantaſticke geſtures in the body, and diſguized lookes in the countenance, as ſo many vlcerous ſcabs of ſuch a ranckling ſore. Wee men are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of our owne faſhions, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of their owne faces, therefore
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:26126:45"/>the one ſeekes to be new ſhaped, and the other to be new dyed. But ô, that men would chuſe <hi>Tertullians</hi> ſtuffe,<note n="c" place="margin">Tertul.</note> 
                  <hi>'<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſtite vos ſerico ſanctitatis, byſſino probitatis, purpura pudicitiae,</hi> Clothe you with the Sattin of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie, the Silke of ſinceritie, and the Purple of puritie. And women, <hi>Gorgonias</hi> complexion: of whom her brother <hi>Nazianzen</hi> reports,<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nazian.</hi> orat. in laud Gorg.</note> 
                  <hi>Vnus iſli placebat rubor quem gignit pudor, vnus candor quem parit abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentia.</hi> The onely red that pleaſed her was the mayden bluſh, the only white the paleneſſe of faſting.</p>
               <p>Oppreſſion is a deuouring gangrene. For as that corrupts and putrifies ſo farre, as that it leaues the member without any thing to keepe life in it: ſo oppreſſion deuoures and waſts ſo long that it leaues a man nothing to maintaine his life vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
               <p>But howſoeuer all iniquitie doth <hi>inquinare,</hi> all ſinne doth ſoyle, yet of all, adultery is commonly, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:26126:46"/>properly to, called the ſinne<note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.21. Col. 3.5. 2 Pet. 2.10.</note> of vncleanneſſe, and is ſaid,<note n="g" place="margin">Pro. 6.33.</note> 
                  <hi>turpitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem congregare,</hi> to gather filth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that commits it. Hence it is, that<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lexicon Theo. D.</hi> Boyes. Fr. Holyoke.</note> 
                  <hi>peccare</hi> is <hi>pellicare,</hi> all ſinne is named of adultery. For as adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is the leauing of a mans owne wife, and going to a<note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 2.16.</note> ſtrange woman (whereupon<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iac.</hi> de vorag.</note> 
                  <hi>adulter, quaſi ad alter</hi>) ſo ſinne is a falling away from God, to whom our ſoule is ioyned in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and a coupling with Satan, with whom wee ought to haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do. Now, if each ſin be a kind of adultery, then adultery hath kinred with each ſinne: and kinred with ſin, is like kinred with ſinners; the neerer the worſer,<note n="l" place="margin">Deut. 7.3.7. 2 King. 8.26.</note> as Scripture ſhewes both in expreſſe words and euident examples.</p>
               <p>This ſinne is one of the principall which defiles the Church of GOD. For it is lamentable to ſee, how men ſtaine and ſpot themſelues with the luſts of the fleſh, whilſt as Beares for a bone, ſo they for the fleſh, doe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:26126:46"/>euen rend and teare one another in pieces. Hence ſo many loathſome diſeaſes in the body; hence ſo many duels and combates in the field; hence ſo many franticke butche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and ſtabbings in the houſe. O that euer valour ſhould come to be proſtituted in ſo vaine a cauſe! But vvee are like<note n="m" place="margin">Vide Iunij adag. Sybar.</note> 
                  <hi>Sybarites,</hi> and haue chaunged manhood into wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſhneſſe, that if <hi>Diogenes</hi> vvere paſſing his iourney from them to vs, he would ſay as once of his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> to the <hi>Athenians,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Diog.</hi> laer. de vit. philo.</note> 
                  <hi>Eo à viris ad foeminas.</hi> I am going from men to very wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. So as a man may ſay to our Gallants, as<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eraſ.</hi> Apoph. lib. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Alexis</hi> to <hi>Calimedon,</hi> Many haue died <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but thou <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, many, for the loue of a Common-wealth, but thou for the loue of a common vvench.</p>
               <p>For remedy hereof, remember <hi>Pauls</hi> words,<note n="p" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.3.</note> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.3. <hi>This is the will of God, euen your ſanctification, that euery one of you ſhould know how
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:26126:47"/>to poſſeſſe his veſſell in holineſſe and honour, and not in the luſt of concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence.</hi> Where marke, how hee bids you keepe your bodies, <hi>viz.</hi> poſſeſſe them. For harlots, and harlot-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers doe not poſſeſſe their bodies themſelues, but ſet them out to hire, and giue poſſeſſion of them to others.</p>
               <p>Againe, marke vvhat he cals the body; a veſſell: euen,<note n="q" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Vas in hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> a veſſell of honour in Gods houſe: but by luſt a man makes it<note n="r" place="margin">Ierem. 1.13.</note> 
                  <hi>ollam ſuccenſam,</hi> a ſeething pot in the Deuils Kitchin, that boyles in the minde. Now, if thy body be in this caſe,<note n="s" place="margin">Ierem. 6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Frigidam fac malitiam,</hi> (there is ſuch a phraſe in <hi>Ieremy</hi>) coole thy naughtineſſe, euen as Cookes doe their pots; and that, eyther by infuſion of water, or by ſubſtraction of vvood, or by remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it from the fire.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I ſay, if the veſſell of thy body boyle ouer vvith luſt, runne to the waters; but not to the waters
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:26126:47"/>which the harlot ſpeakes of,<note n="t" place="margin">Prou. 9.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Stolne waters are ſweet, Prou.</hi> 9.17. but to the vvaters which <hi>Solomon</hi> directed to,<note n="v" place="margin">Prou. 5.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Drinke the water of thine owne Ciſterne, and let them be thine, and not the ſtrangers with thee.</hi> I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that luſt is ſometime compared to water, but that is not a cooling but a kindling water.<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de ciuit. Dei. lib. <hi>21.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> makes mention of a Well in <hi>Epirus,</hi> that, when firebrands vvere put into it, it would quench them: but (which is ſtrange) when they were quenched, would ſet them on fire againe. Such a water is an harlot which quencheth luſt for a time, &amp; ſets the body on fire euer after. Haue therefore a Well of thine own, for<note n="x" place="margin">Pro. 23.27.</note> 
                  <hi>an harlot is as a deepe ditch, and a ſtrange woman as a narrow pit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, if thy concupiſcence be not allayed this way, take away the wood. For<note n="y" place="margin">Eccleſ. 28.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Secundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſyluae ligna exardeſcit ignis, Eccleſ.</hi> 28.10. As is the vvood of the fire ſo is the fire it ſelfe. Now the fewell of luſt is
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:26126:48"/>gluttony and drunkenneſſe.<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de temp. Ser. 69.</note> 
                  <hi>Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per iuncta eſt ſaturitati laſciuia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Saturity is the breeder of impuritie, &amp; fouleneſſe the childe of fulneſſe. See it in <hi>Noah,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Incert. author.</note> 
                  <hi>Noam, qui euaſit aquam, euicit vinum. Noah</hi> that eſcaped the water, could not eſcape the Wine, for wine did make him ſinke, whom water made to ſwimme. See it in <hi>Lot,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen.</hi> in Gen. hom. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Ebrietas decipit quem Sodoma non decipit.</hi> Drunkenneſſe deceiued him whom <hi>Sodome</hi> deceiued not. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ritur ille flammis mulierum, quem ſulphurea flamma non eſsit,</hi> and he is ſcorched with the flames of luſt, that could not be touched with the flames of vengeance. No maruaile then, if vncleanneſſe be ſo hardly auoyded, vvhen drunkenneſſe and gluttony be ſo much affected.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to quench luſt vtterly, remoue thy body quite from the fire: auoyd the company of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſte vvomen. For this by the wiſeſt men hath beene iudged the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:26126:48"/>wiſeſt courſe.<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 39.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> when hee would not haue his Miſtres deſire his company, would not ſo much as offer to be ſeene in her company. <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.10.<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſid.</hi> Peluſ. lib. 2. Epiſt. 62.</note> 
                  <hi>Lectione didici</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſidore</hi> of <hi>Peluſium,</hi> I haue learned by reading, of a certaine King (it was <hi>Antiochus</hi> the third, as I haue learned) who at Epheſus behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the prieſt of <hi>Diana,</hi> (a woman of incomparable beautie) went pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently out of the Citie,<note n="e" place="margin">Id. ib.</note> 
                  <hi>ne praeter voluntatem nefarij aliquid admittere cogeretur.</hi> Leaſt, more then hee was willing to, hee ſhould be tempted to commit vncleaneneſſe with her. And hee addes, that <hi>Cyrus</hi> the great Monarch of <hi>Perſia,</hi> when he had heard of the great Beautie of <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea,</hi> the wife of <hi>Abradalus</hi> King of <hi>Suſa,</hi> hee vvould not yeeld ſo much as to ſee her.<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſid.</hi> Peluſ. vt ſup.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eraſ.</hi> annot. in <hi>Hieron.</hi> Epiſt. ad Innocent.</note> 
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſomewhat tartly, cals adultery <hi>Magnatum ludus,</hi> the ſport
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:26126:49"/>of Nobles. For my part I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeake of <hi>Magnatum laudes,</hi> then <hi>Magnatum ludos,</hi> rather of their praiſe, then of their plaies; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I wiſh that greatnes would not be a patrone to graceleſnes, nor riches a couer for baſe actions. Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is that, vvhich is reported of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the tyrant,<note place="margin">Tacitus.</note> who reprouing his ſonne for deflowring a woman, asked him, if euer hee had heard, that himſelfe, his father, had done any ſuch thing. No, ſaith the young man, and no meruaile, for you had not a King to your father. True, ſaith hee, neither wilt thou haue a King to thy ſonne, if thou ceaſeſt not quickly to follow ſuch courſes as theſe.</p>
               <p>Therefore, great cauſe haue wee to bleſſe God, who hath giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs ſo gracious a King, vvho, as in other vertues hee excels other Kings, ſo in chaſtity, hee excels himſelfe; No doubt, but his roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſonne, our Noble Prince <hi>Charles,</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:26126:49"/>as he was borne of the mirrour of chaſtitie, ſo alſo, (which yet let vs not ceaſe to pray for) he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a mirrour thereof, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of himſelfe, and the admiration of the whole Chriſtian world. And let this ſuffice for the firſt part of my Text. Now to the ſecond.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Open vnto me.</head>
               <p>VVEe haue heard in this ſpeach of Chriſts to his Church, the ſweet words he gaue vnto her; now are we to heare the requeſt which hee deſires of her: which is to <hi>Open vnto him.</hi> Wherein you muſt imagine Chriſt as a louer, ſtanding, or ſitting at the chamber dore of his loue, deſiring to bee let in; Together alſo with an inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome diſlike in his minde, that hee is made to waite ſo long, before he can be receiued in to her.</p>
               <p>As if hee had ſaid, What my
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:26126:50"/>deare Spouſe, doſt thou ſleepe all night, and I thy louer, yea, they Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, here ſhiuer in the colde? ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>my head wet with dew, and my lockes with the drops of the night.</hi> Nay, my deareſt, vſe mee not ſo. Ariſe, <hi>Open vnto mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Temporanoctis eunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ouid.</note> 
                  <hi>excute poſte ſera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 15.12.</note> 
                  <hi>The night is paſt and the day is come,</hi> Vp, let me in; put me on. <hi>Caſt away the workes of darkeneſſe,</hi> and <hi>clothe thee with the armour of light.</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> ſup. Cant. ſerm. 61.</note> 
                  <hi>Hic literalis luſus.</hi> This, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi> is the ſport of the letter. The ſence we muſt further inquire for. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I beſeech you, yet a while to <hi>Open</hi> your cares in attention, whilſt I lay <hi>Open</hi> vnto you the meaning of this word <hi>Open.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A word it is of liberty, and of libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſignification: yet all that in this place it imports may be reduced to two actions. Something, that ſhe is to doe to her children; Something that her children are to do to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:26126:50"/>That which the Church is to doe to her Children, is to Preach Chriſt vnto them,<note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 1.1.</note> which is an opening of the priſon dore, and ſetting the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner at liberty, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. 1. Thus <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> vnderſtands the place,<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in <hi>Iohan.</hi> tract. 57.</note> 
                  <hi>Aperi mihi,</hi> id eſt, <hi>praedica me. Open</hi> vnto me, that is, <hi>Open me;</hi> Preach and declare me.<note n="p" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Ad cos quippe quiclau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt contra me, quomo do intrabo ſine aperiente?</hi> For vnto ſuch as haue ſhut me out, how ſhall I enter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an opener? How ſhall they heare without a<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> Preacher? This thing Chriſt elſe-where deſires of his Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.10.<note n="r" place="margin">Cant. 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſe my loue, my faire one, and come thy way.</hi> Ariſe out of thy bed of contemplation, Come away, looke about, and<note n="s" place="margin">Ioh. 4.35.</note> 
                  <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the regions white vnto harueſt, Ioh.</hi> 4.35. Make haſt and be quicke in preaching. A buſineſſe indeede of important celerity; in reſpect whereof wee muſt paſſe by men<note n="t" place="margin">Luc. 10.4.</note> 
                  <hi>vnſaluted, Luc.</hi> 10 4. And leaue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen our father<note n="u" place="margin">Math. 8.12.</note> 
                  <hi>vnburied. Mat.</hi> 8.22
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:26126:51"/>And it may be, Chriſt therefore a little before his death waſhed his diſciples<note n="v" place="margin">Iohn. 13.15.</note> feete, that they might be nimble, and expedite in preaching, that others ſeeing them, might cry out in admiration<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> 
                  <hi>How beautifull are the feete of them that bring glad tydings of peace, and glad tidings of good things! Rom.</hi> 10.15. Vndoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly a moſt worthy worke of the Church, as can be. Lord Ieſus, let mee euer preach and declare thy name among men, that thou mayſt purge and cleare my name before thy father in heauen.</p>
               <p>Seeing then this buſineſſe of preaching is committed to the Church, it is her duetie to chuſe men that can, and men that will, vndertake ſo weighty a buſineſſe as preaching is: Men that can. For euery blocke is not apt for a <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> nor euery honeſt man to be a teacher. It is<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nazi.</hi> Apol. pag. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>ars artium et ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiarum regere hominem,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen,</hi> an Arte of all Artes and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:26126:51"/>ſciences to be a teacher and ruler of men. Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, he muſt nor be a<note n="z" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Neophyte,</hi> a young Scholler. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprian</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortat. ad marty.</note> 
                  <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> enim idoneus poteſt eſſe miles, qui non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitatus prius in campo fuerit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cyprian.</hi> He can neuer be a fit Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour in Chriſts campe, that was neuer exerciſed in the field before. Which made <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſo pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to complaine, that ſome in his time did<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Figulinam in dolio diſcere.</hi> Gilber. Cog. paraem. 2.7.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as the prouerbe ſaith, that is, as he expounds it, learne knowledge of CHRIST by the deſtruction of ſoules, like vnto bad Phiſitians, who learne skill by hurting their patients. For my part, ſaith hee, I haue euer preferred it as a point of wiſedome,<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nazian.</hi> apol.</note> 
                  <hi>candidam potius aurem ſubmittere, quam ſtolidam linguam mouere.</hi> Rather to vſe an ingenuous eare in hearing, then to moue a blockiſh tongue in ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is the Churches duety to chuſe men that will Preach. For
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:26126:52"/>as good be ſilent with ignorance, as with idleneſſe. And it is no leſſe impietie, not to be willing to Preach when we can, then not to be able to Preach when we ſhould.<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 28.34.</note> 
                  <hi>Moyſes</hi> commanded <hi>Aaron</hi> the high Prieſt, to make him a coate, at the skirts whereof were to be pomegranates of blew ſilke, and bels of Gold, <hi>that his ſound might bee heard, when hee went into the holy place, and when hee went out, that he might not dye. Exod.</hi> 28.34. Hereupon<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg.</hi> Paſt. lib. 2. cap. 14. et Epiſt. lib. 1. ep. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Gregory. Moyſi praecipitur, &amp;c. Moyſes</hi> is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the Prieſt going into the Tabernacle ſhould be compaſſed with bels, that is, <hi>vt voces praedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis habeat,</hi> that hee ſhould haue the voyce of preaching, and ſo not dye.<note n="f" place="margin">Idem vt ſup.</note> 
                  <hi>Sacerdos quippe ingrediens vel egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens moritur, ſi de eo ſonitus non audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur.</hi> For the Prieſt going in and comming out dyeth, if there be no ſound of preaching, nor no ſound preaching come from his mouth. Wherefore let vs bee continually
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:26126:52"/>following our buſineſſe. Let vs, ſaith <hi>Origen</hi> g imitate <hi>Moyſes</hi> and <hi>Aron.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig.</hi> in Leuit. hom. 6.</note> What is ſaid of them? That they departed not out of the Tabernacle day nor night. What did they there? <hi>Aut à Deo aliquid diſcere, aut popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum àocere.</hi> Either learne ſomething of God. or teach ſomething to the people. And, <hi>Haec duo ſunt pontificis opera,</hi> Theſe two things are the whole buſineſſe of a Church-man, either by reading the Scriptures to learne ſomething to himſelfe; or by expounding the Scripture to teach ſomething to the people. And thus much of this.</p>
               <p>The other action I take it, is chiefly intended heere, which each faithfull ſoule, that is a member of the Church, is to doe for it ſelfe, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>Open to Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſpeech indeed metaphoricall: And that you may the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Metaphor, wee muſt call to minde, that man before his fall, being made after the Image of God,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:26126:53"/>had God remayning and abiding in him, as another ſoule to his ſoule, quickning him with another life, which <hi>Paul</hi> cals<note n="h" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.18.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. <hi>the life of God.</hi> And ſo for that time, the ſtate of man in paradiſe was like the happy condition that ſhall be to Gods children in heauen, when<note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.28.</note> GOD ſhall be <hi>all in all,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28. But when by the ſubtiltie of the Diuell, it was mans vnhappy caſe to fall from God, then did hee baniſh and expell that ſweet gueſt out of his ſoule, and was himſelfe expelled and baniſhed out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. And looke how God in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice then, ſhut the gate of Paradiſe againſt man, that hee ſhould not any more come thither: ſo hath man by ſinne, euer ſince, ſhut the dore of his heart againſt God, that hee cannot lodge there. Hence it is, that God who doth neuer ceaſe to ſeeke and to ſaue, doth beg and craue of vs, as in this place, <hi>Open vnto mee,</hi> deſiring that wee againe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:26126:53"/>would entertaine him, that by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing him into our ſoules againe on earth, we may come to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by him into his celeſtiall Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe in heauen.</p>
               <p>Now the dores by which hee is to enter in to vs, are the dores of our ſenſes, and the dores of our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. By the one wee heare and ſee him; by the other wee loue and beleeue in him. And becauſe there is nothing in the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding which is not firſt in the ſenſe, therefore (as I take it) we muſt firſt <hi>Open</hi> the dore of our ſenſes, heare him in the Word, ſee him in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and then, the dores of our vnderſtanding, apprehend him by Faith, and retayne him by Loue.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, <hi>Open</hi> vnto him, that is, <hi>Open</hi> thine eares to heare him prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: a moſt neceſſary worke for a Chriſtian; for,<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith come by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and hearing by the Word of God, Rom.</hi> 10.17. Yea, euen ſuch as haue ſeene Chriſt, and ſeene him cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:26126:54"/>yet haue not beleeued in him by ſeeing, but by hearing. The Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion that watched him at his death,<note n="l" place="margin">Mark. 15.36.</note> 
                  <hi>hearing</hi> him with a cry giue vp the Ghoſt, ſaid, <hi>Truely this was the Sonne of God.</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper. Cant. ſer. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Auditus inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit quod non viſus:</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>Oculum ſpecies fefellit, veritas auri ſe infudit:</hi> His hearing found out that which his ſeeing could not prie into: and Truth ſhewed her ſelfe to his care, that could not be perceiued with his eye. Therefore, God ſaith to his Church,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.11.</note> n <hi>Audi filia &amp; vide,</hi> Heare ô Daughter and ſee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.11.<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> vbi ſup.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid intendis oculum, aurem para;</hi> Why doſt thou bend thine eye, rather prepare thine care, that thou maiſt ſay with them in the <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 48.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Sieut audiuimus ſic vidimus, &amp;c.</hi> As wee haue heard, ſo haue wee ſeene in the Citie of the Lord of Hoaſts, in the Citie of our God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48 8.</p>
               <p>Then, <hi>Open</hi> vnto him, that is, open thine eyes to ſee him cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:26126:54"/>Looke on him in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: in Baptiſme, waſhing and purging thee: in the Lords Supper, feeding and nouriſhing thee. For, theſe are the ſignes which hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to be ſhewed by, and which will make vs, with <hi>Moyſes,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſee him that is inuiſible.</hi> But reſt not in the ſigne, that is but earth, aſpire to that which is ſignified, which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
               <p>To conclude, as<note n="r" place="margin">Dan. 6.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Daniel</hi> ſet his windowes <hi>open</hi> to Ieruſalem, ſo ſet thou thine eyes <hi>open</hi> to heauen,<note n="s" place="margin">Hieron. <hi>ad</hi> Euſtoch.</note> 
                  <hi>vnde lumen introeat</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ierome</hi>) <hi>vnde vide as ciuitatem Domini:</hi> from whence thou maiſt ſee the light of grace, and behold the Citie of God. It is ſaid of God, that<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 34.15.</note> 
                  <hi>his eyes are ouer the righteous, and his eares open to their prayers:</hi> Let thine eyes be toward God, as his are toward thee. Say with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note n="v" place="margin">Pſal. 123.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold, as the eyes of ſeruants looke vnto the hand of their Maſter, and as the eyes of a Mayden vnto the hand of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:26126:55"/>ſo waite our eyes vpon thee O Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou haſt thus heard him, thus ſeene him, let him paſſe from thy ſenſe to thine vnderſtanding. There <hi>open</hi> thine heart to beleeue in him, and thy affections to loue him. Thine heart to beleeue in him: for,<note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 10.10</note> 
                  <hi>With the heart man beleeueth vnto righteouſnes, Rom.</hi> 10.10. And<note n="y" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt doth dwell in the heart by Faith. Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Ianua noſtrafides eſt</hi> (ſaith<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambr.</hi> in Pſal. 118. ſerm. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>quae totam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum ſifuerit robuſta communit.</hi> Faith is the dore which letteth Chriſt into the ſoule, which if it be ſtrong, all the houſe is the ſtronger. And ſtrong it is, if any vertue be ſtrong.<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard.</hi> ſup. Cant. ſerm. 76.</note> 
                  <hi>Attingit inacceſſa, deprehendit ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nota, comprehendit immenſa, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendit nouiſſima:</hi> It toucheth things inacceſſible, findes out things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiueable, apprehends things inviſible, comprehends things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable. Yea, it cloſeth within the ſpheare thereof, euen eternitie
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:26126:55"/>it ſelfe; for that moſt bleſſed and glorious Trinitie, which wee cannot conceiue in our hart by knowledge, wee doe receiue into our ſoules by faith. <hi>Per iſtam ianuam Chriſtus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greditur,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Amb.</hi> in Pſal. 118. ſer. 12.</note> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> By this gate Chriſt enters into the ſoule, and there reſts as in his holy temple. Finally, faith is,<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lud. Viu.</hi> com. in <hi>Aug.</hi> de ciu. dei lib. 1. cap. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>huius vitae viati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi> Our whole prouiſion for this life, without which a man can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> pleaſe God, nor<note n="e" place="margin">Nam qui non placeat deo, non poteſt illi placere deus, <hi>Bern. in Cant. ſer. 24.</hi>
                  </note> God him.</p>
               <p>When thou haſt thus got him by faith, hold him by Loue: For elſe hee will ſoone be gone from thee againe. The two<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rib.</hi> de templ. lib. 1. cap. 21.</note> dores which lead into the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> had ſides round, or folding, and were<note n="g" place="margin">1 King. 6.24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſe inuicem tenentia,</hi> holding or claſping each other: to teach vs, that the two dores of Faith and loue, by which Chriſt Ieſus goes into the ſoule, as into his holy Temple, muſt neuer be ſeparate nor diuided, but muſt <hi>ſe inuicem tenere,</hi> claſpe hands together: becauſe,<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Leo</hi> de collect. &amp; eleemoſ. ſer. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Sicut in fide eſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:26126:56"/>operum ratio, ſic in operibus fidei for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Leo:</hi> Euen as in Faith is the order of our workes, ſo in workes is the life of Faith.</p>
               <p>And thus haue wee heard how wee muſt <hi>open</hi> to him; that we may the better doe it, let vs ſee how he knockes for enterance, and why. For the firſt, vnderſtand that God knockes at the gate of our heart, for lodging there, diuers wayes. Firſt,<note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> by the open voyce of the miniſterie, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>We pray you euen as if God did beſeech you through vs, that yee be reconciled vnto God.</hi> Secondly, by wholeſome inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Reu.</hi> 3.20.<note n="k" place="margin">Reu. 3.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold, I ſtand at the doore and knocke, if any man will heare my voyce, and open vnto mee, I will come in to him, and ſup with him. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> (ſaith<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> confeſs. lib. 10. cap. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>amo te, percuſſiſticor meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; amaui te:</hi> Lord, I loue thee, thou haſt knocked at my heart, and I haue ſet my minde on thee. And<note n="m" place="margin">Acts 17.27.</note> doubtleſſe he is not farre from euery one of vs. Not
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:26126:56"/>farre, no,<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Senec.</hi> epiſt. 41</note> 
                  <hi>Prope eſt à te Deus, tecum eſt, intus eſt,</hi> ſaith diuine <hi>Seneca.</hi> God is neere thee, with thee, within thee. <hi>Ita dico,</hi> Lucili, <hi>ſacer intra nos Spiritus ſedet.</hi> Yea, it is, as I ſay, there is an holy ſpirit reſting in vs, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not reſting, but ſtirring &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs to holy actions.<note n="o" place="margin">Idi. bid.</note> 
                  <hi>Bonus vir ſine deo nemo eſt,</hi> ſo impoſſible is it for any man to be good without God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by the Creatures: the world is a Booke, Heauen and earth opened leaues, each creature a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to teach vs to know and to loue God:<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> confeſs. lib. 1. cap. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Domine</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>&amp; coelum &amp; terra, &amp; omnia quae in eis ſunt, ecce vndi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mihi dicunt vt te amem, nec ceſſant dicere omnibus, vt ſint inexcuſabiles.</hi> Heauen and earth, and all things therein, lo, (ô Lord) they all ſpeake to me to loue thee, and ſo they doe to all other men, to make them without excuſe. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by afflictions. And then God knockes vs ſomewhat hard indeed. For, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith,<note n="q" place="margin">Iob 33.15.16</note> 
                  <hi>God ſpeakes once
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:26126:57"/>or twice, &amp; one ſeeth it not, in dreames and viſions of the night: Then he ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth their eares, euen by their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections which he hath ſealed.</hi> So that God <hi>Opens</hi> mens eares to heare his call, and then men <hi>Open</hi> their harts to let him in.</p>
               <p>But why (Lord) why doſt thou beg thus of vs to let thee in? Art not thou able to make enterance thy ſelfe? Is our heart harder then that<note n="r" place="margin">Act. 12.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Iron gate</hi> of the Citie, which <hi>opened</hi> vnto <hi>Peter</hi> of its own accord? And art not thou our <hi>Sampſon,</hi> able to breake vp, and breake downe the<note n="s" place="margin">Iudg. 16.3.</note> gates of our <hi>Azzah,</hi> and to carry them with thee into thy holy mountaine? Laſtly, haſt not thou the Key of <hi>Dauid,</hi> which<note n="t" place="margin">Reuel. 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>openeſt, and no man ſhutteth, which ſhutteſt and no man openeth?</hi> Why doſt thou then beg ſo much to haue vs <hi>Open</hi> to thee, thou being ſo well able to <hi>Open</hi> to thy ſelfe?</p>
               <p>Yes my deare brethren, God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of vs to let him in, becauſe his
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:26126:57"/>preſence is not pleaſing to himſelfe, if it be not pleaſing vnto vs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would haue vs <hi>Open</hi> to him, receiue him willingly, entertaine him ioyfully, that ſo hee may ioy to remaine with vs. For, it is his<note n="v" place="margin">Prou. 8.31.</note> 
                  <hi>delight to be with the ſonnes of men,</hi> eſpecially if they againe delight to be with him. And hence it is, that wee haue ſo many ſweet exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,<note n="u" place="margin">Eph. 4.30.</note> 
                  <hi>not to grieue his ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.19</note> 
                  <hi>not to quench the ſpirit:</hi> but to<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 31.23.</note> 
                  <hi>loue the Lord,</hi> and <hi>to</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 37.4.</note> 
                  <hi>delight in him.</hi> And all for this end, that hee might pleaſe himſelfe in the kinde enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment that comes from vs. For hee tarryes with no man againſt his will, nor remaines in any place where he is not welcome.</p>
               <p>Therefore, he is not more ready to demaund entertainment of vs, then hee is forward to giue abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the thing vnto vs. For,<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 15.5.</note> 
                  <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him can wee doe nothing.</hi> As no man but Chriſt could<note n="b" place="margin">Reu. 5.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Open</hi> the claſped Booke, that Gods counſels
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:26126:58"/>might be deliuered to vs; ſo none but Chriſt can <hi>Open</hi> our cloſed heart, that Gods counſels might be receiued of vs. Euen he which bids vs <hi>Open</hi> to him, muſt <hi>Open</hi> for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: Our heart, as hee did the<note n="c" place="margin">Acts 16.14.</note> hart of <hi>Lydia, Acts</hi> 16.14. Our<note n="d" place="margin">Luke 24.31.</note> wits, as the two Diſciples that went to <hi>Emmaus, Luke</hi> 24.31. Our eyes, as the<note n="e" place="margin">Mar. 10.47.</note> eyes of blinde <hi>Bartimaus, Marke</hi> 10.47. Our eares, as the eares<note n="f" place="margin">Mar. 7.34.</note> of the deafe and dumbe man, <hi>Marke</hi> 7.34. <hi>Domine</hi> (ſaith<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> confeſs. lib. 10. cap. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, vocaſti, &amp; clamaſti, &amp; ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſti ſur ditat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m meam:</hi> Lord, thou haſt called, thou haſt cryed, and beate through my deafneſſe.<note n="h" place="margin">Id. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſcaſti &amp; ſplenduiſti, &amp; fugaſti ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatem meam:</hi> Thou haſt glittered, thou haſt ſhined, and driuen away my blindneſſe. Then Lord, giue what thou commandeſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what thou wilt.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, to draw to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, and to ſhut vp this word <hi>Open,</hi> remember what Chriſt ſaith
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:26126:58"/>vnto you here, <hi>Open vnto mee.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what you muſt ſay to Chriſt hereafter, <hi>Open vnto vs:</hi> that which you ſhall deſire of him then, that doe, whilſt hee requeſts it of you now.</p>
               <p>Gouernours and Rulers, heare what is ſaid of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 29.3<note n="i" place="margin">1 Chron. 29.3</note> 
                  <hi>Hee opened the dores of the houſe of the Lord</hi> (which<note n="k" place="margin">2 Chr. 28.24</note> 
                  <hi>Ahaz</hi> had ſhut) <hi>in the firſt yeere of his raigne, and the firſt moneth of the yeere.</hi> Hee began to ſettle his owne kingdome with the ſetting vp Gods Kingdome, and ſo fulfilled the requeſt of each faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoule, that had cryed out with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 118.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Open me the gates of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, that I may goe in, and praiſe the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yee Reuerend Fathers, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Church, remember what is ſaid of Chriſt,<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 5.2.</note> 
                  <hi>He opened his mouth and taught, Mat.</hi> 5.2. which ſignifies, eyther that hee ſpake of<note n="n" place="margin">Apertio oris profunditatem ſignificat ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti. <hi>Strab. in Gloſs. ad loc.</hi>
                  </note> high matters, according to that of <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.35.<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 13.35.</note> 
                  <hi>I will
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:26126:59"/>open my mouth in Parables, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare hard ſentences of old:</hi> or elſe, that hee ſpake boldly and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, accordng to that of <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 29.21. <hi>In that day I</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Ezek. 29.21.</note> 
                  <hi>will giue thee an open mouth in the midſt of them.</hi> And this being remembred, will vntie the ſtrings of their tongues, whoſe mouthes ſeeme to be coped vp like Ferrets, and can ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all: or whoſe practiſe is<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen.</hi> in Gen. hom. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Linire parietem lapſantem,</hi> as <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> ſpeakes, to daube a tottering wall, and colour ouer their ſinnes, with ſilent ouer-paſſing, which they ſhould rub out with ſharpe repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
               <p>Ye worſhipfull Magiſtrates and Iudges. Heare what <hi>Bethſheba</hi> ſaith to her ſonne. <hi>Prou.</hi> 31.8.<note n="r" place="margin">Prou. 31.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Open thy mouth for the dumbe in the cauſe of all the children of deſtruction.</hi> Remember that ye be liuing lawes, to teach men by your actions, as vvell as by your counſailes. And one day we ſhall all appeare before
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:26126:59"/>the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt.<note n="s" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> Epiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Vbi plus valebunt pura corda quam aſtuta verba, &amp; conſcientia bona, quam marſupia plena.</hi> When a pure heart ſhall do more then a ſubtile tongue, and a good conſcience preuaile aboue a full purſe.</p>
               <p>Ye rich men, Remember what God ſaith to his people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.8.<note n="t" place="margin">Deut. 15.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſhut thy hand from thy brother, but thou ſhalt Open thy hand vnto him.</hi> And to conclude all, you that are tradeſmen, as you <hi>Open</hi> you ſhops to men for gaine, ſo <hi>Open</hi> your hearts to Chriſt for godlineſſe,<note n="v" place="margin">Heb. 9.8.</note> Chriſt hath <hi>Opened</hi> to vs a way into the holy of holies. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.8. Shall Chriſt <hi>Open</hi> a way for vs in heauen, and ſhall not we <hi>Open</hi> a way for him on earth? Yes: As<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 8.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Noah Opened</hi> the window of his arke and tooke in the <hi>Doue,</hi> that came flying to him with an Oliue leafe in her mouth: ſo let vs <hi>Open</hi> the dore of our heart, and receiue Gods <hi>Doue,</hi> his bleſſed ſpirit, that
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:26126:60"/>brings the Oliue of peace vvith him.</p>
               <p>Finally, let me ſay to each mans heart, which is the gate of his ſoule, as <hi>Dauid</hi> doth to the gates of the Temple. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 24.9.<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 24.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Lift your heads O ye gates, and be ye lift vp ye euerlaſting dores, and the King of Glory ſhall goe in.</hi> Let the King of glory come into our ſoules now, that wee may come into his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of glory hereafter. To which King of glory, One eternall, and euer-liuing God, and three perſons, the father, ſonne, and holy Ghoſt, be all glory, might, Maieſty, power and dominion for euer and euer <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26126:60"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
